<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Political and military observations, remarks and maxims, of Charles V. late duke of Lorrain, general of the Emperor's forces From a manuscript left by him, and never printed before.</title>
            <author>Charles V, Duke of Lorraine, 1643-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 153 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200475</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895385</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895385</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79400)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2330:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Political and military observations, remarks and maxims, of Charles V. late duke of Lorrain, general of the Emperor's forces From a manuscript left by him, and never printed before.</title>
                  <author>Charles V, Duke of Lorraine, 1643-1690.</author>
                  <author>Beck, Rupert.</author>
                  <author>Savage, John, fl. 1680, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 277, [9] p. [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Jones at the Dolphin and Crown in S. Paul's Church-yard, and W. Hawes at the Rose in Ludgate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Rupert Beck.</note>
                  <note>With four final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>With frontis. woodcut port. of Charles V signed "I. Savage sculp."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Political</hi> and <hi>Military</hi> OBSERVATIONS, REMARKS AND MAXIMS, OF Charles V. Late Duke of <hi>LORRAIN,</hi> General of the Emperor's Forces. From a <hi>Manuſcript</hi> left by him, and never Printed before.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Juſtum bellum quibus neceſſarium, &amp; pia arma quibus nulla niſi in armis relinquitur Spes.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tit. Liv.</hi> hiſt. l. <hi>9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Jones</hi> at the <hi>Dolphin</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, and <hi>W. Hawes</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable <hi>ARNOLD JUSTE,</hi> Earl of <hi>Albemarle,</hi> Viſcount of <hi>Berry,</hi> Baron of <hi>Keppel</hi> and <hi>Aſhford,</hi> Maſter of his Majeſty's. Wardrobe, General of the <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> and Major General of the Horſe in the Service of the States General of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOT only the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Princes, but the greateſt Monuments of their Glory, have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, excepting their good Works, and wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:152881:3"/>Sayings, which Fame hath handed to Poſterity from one Age to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Thus are come to light the Papers of <hi>Charles</hi> the V. late Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> General of the Emperor's Forces Writ by him. I, thought it Injuſtice to confine them amongſt my Papers, therefore have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to give his Thoughts an Engliſh Dreſs, they were never Printed till now. This Country, where he was a Stranger, is the firſt Place in which they ſee light; where having need of a
<pb facs="tcp:152881:3"/>Noble Protector, I took the Liberty to preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt your Lordſhip with the Tranſlation in Manuſcript, and thereby had recourſe to your Lordſhip's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that this Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Stranger's Spare-hours might find that ſhelter and Countenance, which his great Character calls for.</p>
            <p>This Prince was ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that he could never find leiſure to be idle, even in his Retirements from Affairs he would have ſome Subject to imploy himſelf. It is obſervable that the nobleſt Works of
<pb facs="tcp:152881:4"/>the Creation are moſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: Activity was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to him, that the Sun might as well ſtand ſtill, or the Sea ceaſe from its Motion, as this Prince deſiſt from giving himſelf Imployment.</p>
            <p>You will find, my Lord, that Variety that may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert; they being Miſcella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that give more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, than a continued Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Matter. Theſe will be acceptable to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, eſpecially to ſuch who to this day, make his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Subject of their Converſations.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:4"/>
            <p>His Notions and Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims carry Worth in them, ſo may deſerve your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Protection, they need no Encomiums. And though ſome may not have the like Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of this Prince's Works, yet it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that he was a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and that they dropt from the Pen of a Prince.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scotch</hi> Hiſtory tells us, That one of their Kings, while confined, did ſcratch with his Nails the Hiſtory of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Paſſion on the Wall; which rough Draught be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done by Princely
<pb facs="tcp:152881:5"/>Hands, was more preferra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than what might have been done of that kind by the moſt celebrated Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <p>He was not only valued for his Illuſtrious Birth, as being of the beſt Bloud of Chriſtendom, but reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced for his great Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, for which his Perſon was had in ſo great Eſteem, and intitled to double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; for he was not only born a Prince, but was alſo an experienced Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. Such was his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Perfections, that each were ſo many Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalizers of his Fame;
<pb facs="tcp:152881:5"/>and, with the old Hero's, he hath ſcattered his Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies in the Fields of Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, of whom Fame hath muſtered Catalogues, and with them he hath filled the World with Applauſe; ſo that the Chronicles are ſo many ſtanding Records to his and their Glory: For the Exploits of War have ſomething of more ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour in them, than thoſe of Peace.</p>
            <p>Theſe retired Thoughts, which his Memory hath regiſt'red from Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Practice, are given to the Publick, as I found them, to change their
<pb facs="tcp:152881:6"/>Form, would have been preſumptuous. The Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Civility and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, that appeared in the courſe of his Life, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves here in this Treatiſe. In his own Country, they need no Protection; his Fame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo celebrated, though his Conceptions are Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers there. As his Perſon fled for refuge to <hi>Germany,</hi> ſo his Works do now to your Lordſhip for Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary from the ill Uſage of a Cenſorious and inhoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table World; though his Actions are ſo many Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of his Fame, yet
<pb facs="tcp:152881:6"/>they need your noble Protection; which I am the more incouraged to ſupplicate, in that you will find many Things not unknown to your early Experience. And though Things have daily impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſince his Time, yet here are never dying Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, that will be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Uſe in all Ages.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>You are one of thoſe from whom this Age ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects great Things; for you did early promiſe ſo much, which makes that, the Eyes of all are upon you, who with me wiſh,
<pb facs="tcp:152881:7"/>that Fortune may always ſmile upon you: That as you have advanced in the Temple of Honour, ſo you may in Favour with God and our great King, to the Good of the Nation, the Honour of your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and Illuſtrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and the great Joy of,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
                     <signed> Your Lordſhip's moſt humble, and moſt obedient Servant, <hi>Rupert Beck.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:7"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THis Work is of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that generous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires may thereby be ingendered in the Reader. The Subject is Peace and War, Civil and Foreign, with Obſervations according to the Nature of the Subject. Here are alſo Maxims drawn from Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Each may here find what is required in their different Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, from the General to the
<pb facs="tcp:152881:8"/>Common Souldier, who through a generous Emulation may raiſe his Fortune.</p>
            <p>Here are Precepts for Peace and War, amongſt which are ſeveral Things, that ſpeak our Prince diſpleaſed, and in a complaining Tone of ſome hard <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage, which he thought he had received from a Great Monarch, between whom there was ſome Miſunderſtanding. Without doing wrong to his Memoirs, I could not omit his Expreſſions; but ſome Grains of allowance may be had to the Circumſtances he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured under, having to do with ſo Potent a Neighbour, That not only our Author, but
<pb facs="tcp:152881:8"/>even all <hi>Europe</hi> hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmed at the great Progreſs his Arms have made. And to ſpeak the Truth, Great hath been the Advantage that the Houſe of <hi>France</hi> hath had from this their preſent Monarch's ſo long Reign; who, to do him juſtice, were he not a King, yet is he Great in his own Perſon, and wonderfully qualifyed to ſit at the Helm of Empire, being ſo much Maſter of the Art of Reigning.</p>
            <p>By the Obſervations that are found here, all Perſons, in whatever Province they move in, may find that which will affect them, ſo as to be fearleſs in War, happy in
<pb facs="tcp:152881:9"/>Peace, and to reign in the Hearts of Friends and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: And to be loved, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and feared, ſo that they may ſay with <hi>M. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius,</hi> That where Vertue hath acquired the Love and Affections of the Subjects, that there can be no want of Men or Treaſure.</p>
            <p>To conclude, the whole here may be ſeen, how to act in Peace and War, ſo that in Adverſity or Proſperity they may neither preſume, nor deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152881:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Political</hi> and <hi>Military <hi>Obſervations, Remarks,</hi>
               </hi> AND <hi>MAXIMS,</hi> OF CHARLES V. Late Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>PEace is that tranquil, and ſedate State, where all things did breath gently, lived quietly, and moved in an harmonious Order; till it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted by <hi>Lucifer,</hi> when he rebelled againſt his Maker, and ſeduced Man; and as he loſt Heaven for himſelf, ſo he occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned Man to be turned out of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152881:10"/>his primitive peaceable Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who, by ſiding with the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer, did intail miſery on his Poſterity, who were made Slaves before they knew what Liberty was.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Adam</hi> intail'd on his Poſterity, to be exerciſed with all manner of Evils; ſo that Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſeems but a Shadow, an airy, imaginary Nothing, which while we think we graſp, it ſcapes us. Theſe are the ſad Effects of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Corruption, from whence came all the Diſſenſions private, and publick, that juſtle out Peace at Home, and Abroad, with God, and with Man; ſo that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Country could boaſt of being exempted from this ſad Fate, but ſooner or later hath had the turn of the Wheel from Peace to War, which by intervals have ſucceeded each
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152881:10"/>other: This is the Subject on which I will make ſome Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their Order. And firſt</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Peace.</head>
               <p>WHich is one of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Bleſſings of this Life, as being the Treaſury of temporal Felicities, and is as Youth to Age, Light to Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and as Health is in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Sickneſs: It is the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bleſſing, and was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's laſt Legacy, <hi>my Peace I give unto you.</hi> The Angels could not find a better Wiſh for Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in their Anthem to the Shepheards, than that of Peace, which is the Calm in oppoſition to Tempeſt, and order to Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and is the Summer that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152881:11"/>makes every thing Floriſh. This Sovereign Bleſſing, where it is extended, ſpreadeth its Wings not only over particular Perſons, but even whole Nations are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced ſo by it, that their Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Flow with Milk and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; and through its bonds of Concord, and Union, People and Countries are kept and linked together in Amity; and every thing where it Reigns is thereby increaſed ſo, that each may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy themſelves, and their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies under the Shadow of their own Vine, and Reap the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their Labours, and ſo Live on the Fatneſs of the Earth, by which they are Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and Maintained; whereas War is the Conſumer and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of all. Peace is ſo Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable, that Triumphs are not to be compared to it, which though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152881:11"/>it were an unjuſt one, yet is it more deſirable than a juſt War; ſo that they who have two Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, would part with one to procure it, that thereby they may Live in quiet. This Peace is a Bleſſing never valued till gone: It is like harmony in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, the Diſturbers of which, ought to be Cut off as Enemies to Mankind, and numbered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Wicked, whoſe Death is the ſafety of the Good. No Treaſure can be better im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed than for its Preſervation; ſuch only deſire not Peace, that would profit by Fiſhing in troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Waters: It makes ſmall things increaſe, when by diſcord Men are hurried and precipitated to the greateſt Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>They deſerve Cenſure that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve themſelves in an uncertain War in expectation of an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152881:12"/>Good; by changing Peace for War, in expectation of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good, they expoſe to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery all that are Imbarked in it with them. This is turning our backs againſt our own Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and opening a Door to Deſtruction. But ſuch is Man's unhappy tranſitory State, that there is nothing ſo deſirable but time may find a cauſe to dislike it; nor is any ſo in Health, nor ſo Strong, but they may expect a change: There is not ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative in Nature that can ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Corruption, but it will grow in the Body politick as well as in the Humane; ſo that one Hour hath ſometimes produced great alterations: Therefore as the one hath its Preſcriptions for Health, ſo hath the other its Preſervative which is Religion; wherefore it is here recommended, as the beſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152881:12"/>bottom, to eſtabliſh the Health and Peace of the Commonweale; for where Religion does Reign, there good Government and Peace is liklieſt to Floriſh.</p>
               <p>Though there be no fence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Viciſſitudes, yet a well-conſtituted Government may conduce much to prevent alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, whether in respect of its</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſtical, Civil,</hi> or <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary</hi> State. All which have a natural Dependence on each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and though <hi>Religion</hi> be out of the Province of a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, yet ſhall I adventure to Speak my Thoughts of its uſe, as being ſo neceſſary an ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to obtain the deſired End, <hi>viz.</hi> good Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Religion</hi> is the foundation of a Commonwealth, without which, a Government cannot Subſiſt, but will fall to Decay; there can
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152881:13"/>be no ſurer ſign of its Ruine, than when it is Contemned: It is the true and well-tempered Cement that links, unites and binds together, and ought to be the firſt thing that ſhould be imbibed by Men. Without Religion, there can be no ſettled Government Eſtabliſhed, which may ſufficiently evidence its Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
               <p>Therefore thoſe that intend to be obeyed, muſt before all things prefer the ſettling Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in their Country, as being that which hath the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the Spirits of the People to charm them to Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; It is a holy Policy to make Men ſtoop to the Magiſtrates, and is the Bridle, and a Reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on even to Heathens, who are more Zealous Obſervers of their Laws, and more obedient, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152881:13"/>may ſame Chriſtian Rulers as well as People. It may not be a Digreſſion to obſerve here, That though a Prince may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in matters of Religion from his Sujects, yet Prudence requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of him, for his and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to ſuffer the Religion of the Country; for Mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence are gently to be let, not driven and impoſed on. The little Foxes that ſpoil the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard are to be taken, not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troyed, Arguments, and good Examples are better Nets to take the Multitude, than Fire and Faggots; the impoſing on Mens Conſciences is a ſort of Tyranny, and a vain attempting to ſcale Heaven by wordly Ladders. But where a Prince is bigotted by his Levites, he is carried away even to the eclipſing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manning of his Perſon, by whoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152881:14"/>Inſtigations he becomes a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant over Conſciences, and is an Uſurper of God's Prerogative, who will only Reign there. A Prince ought not to be poſſeſſed with the Spirit of Perſecution, as being not at all becoming his Character: For there is no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that hath not thoſe that would not Sacrifice their all in teſtimony of the Truth, of what they profeſs; and though they differ, yet they all agree in this, that their Scope and ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate End is Heaven; neither is it material whether we go one way, or the other, ſo we get but thither. To ſhew a Traveller the beſt and ſafeſt way to his Journey's end, is not to uſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion or Blows; but with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and Gentleneſs, and by well-wiſhing Motives, ſhewing the advantages of the one, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152881:14"/>the dangers, and inconveniences of the other, and reſt there, without being ſo anxiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned that any particular Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents be followed above the reſt. Alſo it may be an induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to conſider, That the Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Religion is a great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to trading Countries. If you diſturb the Bees, they will leave of carrying in Wax and Honey, and betake themſelves to another Place, where they may do it with more ſafety. Thus, as by not ſuffering Liberty, many floriſhing Countries have been Impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and Depopulated; ſo, on the other hand, Liberty is the Inricher and Incourager of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the Increaſer of Wealth, and number of People, in which conſiſts a Prince's Riches, as well as Safety.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152881:15"/>
               <p>And to ſpeak as a Man of the World unacquainted with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sentiments for Piety that Duty requires, who beholds all Religions a like, and looks upon them to be no more than a jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Invention, contrived to muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle the Subjects, and keep them in Awe, yet ought he not to ſlight thoſe ſacred Artifices, though his Conſcience may not move, yet let Policy induce him. For it is a Prince's Worldly, as well as Spiritual intereſt to be moderete in injoyning his Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in matters of Religion; and if he thinks that Religion is prejudicial to his Prerogative, yet let him at leaſt retain the ſhadow of it, and conſider that external Holineſs procures awful Regards, and that it is both an inward and outward Charmer. Therefore let a Countrey always
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152881:15"/>have ſuch Spiritual Leaders as are true, and not pretended Chaplains to the Prince of Peace; ſuch Torches as are ſaving Lights, not Firebrands, whoſe Tempers are mild and ſoft, and whoſe Breathings are pacificatory.</p>
               <p>A good Government is a good foundation for Peace, which is likelieſt to floriſh, where Reaſon and Religion Reigns; it requires no leſs Prudence to preſerve Peace, than Valour to obtain it. That Countrey is liklieſt to be beſt preſerved, where the Prince knows how to Govern, and the People to Obey: That place is Happieſt where the Subject feareth to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, without which reſtraint, Commonwealths would prove but ſo many unweildly ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable Bodies. In order to a well conſtituted State, two things are requir'd, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152881:16"/>
               <head>Rewards and Puniſhments.</head>
               <p>WIthout a due Diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which, according to the Merit or Demerits of the Perſons concerned, Virtue will flag, and Vice predominate. That Prince who Rewads nothing, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes nothing: Where Valour and Merit meets not with due incouragements, Men will be unwilling to attempt notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their Courage; for it is certain, that Benefits well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed eſtabliſh a Kingdom, when Services unrewarded unhinge it: For as Wiſdom and Courage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets admiration in a Prince, ſo Veracity, Courteſie, and Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity do ſtir up and awaken the Subjects Affections.</p>
               <p>Alſo Princes and Magiſtrates ſhould incourage noble Actions,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152881:16"/>Arts and Inventions, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Trade, as being the true means to inrich the People. Thus the Princes and Subjects Intereſt ſhould be the ſame, without by reſpects; the Princes good being the Peoples, and the Peoples the Princes.</p>
               <p>He Reigns beſt that Reigns as he ought, and though placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſt in the ſeat of Soveraignity, yet ſhould he condeſcend, and take cognizance, and look down on the Humble and Oppreſſed; the redreſſing whoſe Grievances is as much his Honour as Safety. His Ear ſhould be always open to the Cries of Complainants, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from the rapine of Oppreſſors, and his Heart full of Compaſſion; lending one Hand to ſupport, and the other to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge their Injuries. It is a moſt unhapy thing for a Prince, when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152881:17"/>the People are always upon the complaining Key; he muſt needs be in a perpetual Anxiety and Fear, and conſtantly upon the Tenters, ſeeking ways to ſecure himſelf. For God hath been ſo Merciful to Mankind, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſafe for a Prince, but what is Honeſt and Juſt; whoſe Security depends on his good Government, by which means Glory is acquired, and his world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Intereſt ſecured: When on the contrary, from Evil conduct accrue Diſgrace and Shame, and thereby all is expoſed to Ruine. It is very juſtly, that good or evil Managements are attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Prince; he being the Soul to the Body, from whom the reſt of the Members receive Light and Vigour, or as the Spring that gives Motions to the reſt of the Work.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152881:17"/>
               <p>In order to Reign Peaceably and Honourably, with ſecurity to both Prince and People; there muſt be a ſtrict Hand of Juſtice Maintained: For where that is Obſtructed there neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follows a depravation of Manners, and a juſtling out of Faith, Honour and Morality; by which a Door is opened to Licentiouſneſs; to prevent which <hi>Trajanus</hi>'s Example is a great expedient, who would make choice of none to ſit at the Helm, but the Wiſe, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Good; nor would he place in Military Imployments any, but ſuch as were experienced, and of known Courage and Conduct: Even his Courtiers had the Character of being Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, Debonair and Courteous.</p>
               <p>But it is too Common to have ſuch put in Places of Truſt as are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152881:18"/>Unfit; the Obſervation of which cauſed <hi>Caligula</hi> to propoſe the making his Horſe Burgermaſter of <hi>Rome;</hi> alledging, That ſo beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful a Beaſt might as well become that Station, as ſome of thoſe plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there; and would be a leſs detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Publick, whoſe Faults they need not fear would hurt the Citizens. A modeſt Reproof, and an Advertiſement for time to come, to make choice of more fit Inſtruments, than that of Men that act like Beaſts. Experience hath ſhewn in all Ages, how fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal the Choice of unfit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hath been to the common Good, of which the Avarice of thoſe that have had the diſpoſal of Places was the occaſion: For as they have purchaſed at a dear Rate, and came in without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of perſonal Merit; ſo they ſell Offices by retail: Thus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152881:18"/>Money is the Qualification, and the greateſt Ignorants may thus be preferred before Men of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: But great Good accrues to that Government where uſeful Inſtruments are choſen, whoſe Buſineſs ſhall be to promote the publick Good, in oppoſition to Flatterers, ſuch who are unby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed, whoſe Fidelity neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, nor Threats can unhinge. But where thoſe Caterpillers, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Flatterers, bear ſway, no Good can be expected; much better it is to fall amongſt ravenous Birds, than into the Clutches of ſuch Harpies: It may be ſaid of ſome, as it was ſaid of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that he govern'd the World, but that <hi>Foſtina</hi> govern'd him; ſo Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, when they have gained an aſcendant over the Prince, that though he governs the People, yet they over-rule him. It was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152881:19"/>Pope <hi>Pius</hi> II.'s complaint on his Death-bed, when his Sycophants gave him hopes of Recovery, that the miſery that attended Princes was great, ſince they could not hear Truth from thoſe about them, though at a time when the Knowledge of it was moſt uſeful. Theſe flattering Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites are the Plagues of Princes Courts, and with Juſtice deſerve the Epithet, as having no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion but Self-intereſt, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for God their Mammon, to whom they are more faithful than to their Soveraign. It is to that Idol, and to Greatneſs, that they pay Adoration, nor will they Know any other Deity, but they make them their ultimate End. How do Princes hereby make themſelves contemptible? And are expos'd to the cenſure of being puſillanimous for being thus led
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152881:19"/>at pleaſure; which ſpeaks their want of Courage as well as a Deficiency of other Regal and Princely Qualifications; which occaſions that Remiſneſs, and Lenity by which they are expoſed to be cheated: It is alſo an inlet to Irregularities, that gives an occaſion to think as if they feared to do Juſtice, leſt they offend thereby their Paraſites; thus not only the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured Subject ſuffers, but alſo the Prince in the Opinion of his Subjects.</p>
               <p>It is alſo very eſſential to the Preſervation of the Peace, and Proſperity of a People, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be their example of good, as being their Looking-glaſs, whoſe Examples are Precepts, whether good or evil; which work more upon the Vulgar than National Laws. Therefore they ſhould be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152881:20"/>bright and ſhining Lights, to lead the way to Virtue; the ſame ſhould be all thoſe they intruſt with Power, without which they will be but ſo many <hi>Ignes fatui,</hi> that lead the Ignorant a-ſtray; where Virtue is not the Standard, there Common-wealths are made the feat of Vice, which might have been the ſtage of Virtue.</p>
               <p>It is the Stay of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that the Magiſtate knows to uſe his Authority; for the Eyes of each are on him as a publick Dial that regulates adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Clocks; ſo Subjects ſteer their Actions according to their Morals; and though there may be Reaſons for repealing and changing Laws, yet while they ſtand in force, they ſhould not be ſuffered to be broken, that it give not occaſion to have them contemned; and ſo become of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152881:20"/>no more effect, than ſo many Scare-crows with which thoſe Birds, whom they ſhould baniſh, become familiar even to pearch upon the Head of what before was their terror; having by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience learned, That they are no more than toothleſs Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears. It is not ſufficient to have wholeſome Laws, but they muſt be put in practice to reſtrain the Diſorderly. For there are a ſort of reſtleſs Men never ſatify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, no not even with their own Choice, ſuch who like the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow always oppoſe the Sun Be the Government what it will, they are for contradiction ſtill, aſpiring after what they enjoy not. Theſe are the eternal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimers againſt all reigning Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſhments, and are the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes in a Common-wealth, which, as gangrened Members, ought to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152881:21"/>be removed, or cut off for the good of the Body. They are the Vermine, Excrements, and Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſances, of whom Nature ſhould diſcharge itſelf as of a common grievance; following the preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of that Prince who, would have that Horſe killed, whoſe fiery Temper gave diſquiet to his Camerades. With more Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, factious Men ought to be examplarily puniſhed, as being the more dangerous ſort of Brutes, whoſe reſtleſs Tempers would be of worſe conſequence were they ſuffered to take Root, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould be early mowed down, or nipt in their Bud: Or at leaſt their Sting ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them, that their Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may not ſwell that Part they would affect. Lenity in a Prince on ſuch Occaſions, may be of ill conſequence to the Publick; and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152881:21"/>as Tyranny may be fatal, ſo may Lenity be the ruin of a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And though a Prince may not find it neceſſary to ſee, nor hear all he may ſee, or hear, and that Prudence will, that he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the Knowledge of many Things; yet there is a time that Juſtice muſt take Place, That evil may be reſtrained, but ſo as to prevent Deſpair; leſt the Exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated finding all hopes exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhould awaken Revenge to the deſperately overturning all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: For as Oppreſſion weakens the Government, ſo that Prince loſes his Reputation, when he retaineth no more of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Qualities than the name, and pomp of State, that outward appearence gives him. Where a Prince is loved, feared and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there the Government thriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and Floriſhes; for in Union
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152881:22"/>conſiſts the Strenght of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Politick, who as our Bodies are compoſed of ſeveral Parts, each having aſſigned them their different Offices for the good of the Whole, to which order they all ſubmit and agrees; ſo that if one Part or Member is offended, the other participates, and are not angry at each others Acts: But if a foreign Power wound an Eye, tread on a Toe, or hurt a Finger, the whole Body ſhall be affected ſo, as to diſcover each their Reſentments. How will the Eye ſhew its anger, the Noſe ſhrink, the Mouth exclaim, and the Hands fly to the aſſiſtance of the grieved Part? The Feet, even the whole Body, according to the danger, take the alarm. Thus each Part ſympathiſes, in the common Good or Evil that relate to the whole: Thus each one
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152881:22"/>ſhould be concerned for the common Good of that Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick of which they are Members. It is obſervable, That amongſt irrational Creatures, there is not found that diſcord as amongſt Men; they do not devour and deſtroy thoſe of their own kind, in which Men are worſe than the worſt of Brutes; for they tear and devour each other, in which their Shame they glory.</p>
               <p>For the promoting this Union, the Prince ſhould be circumſpect, patient, and quick in diſpatches, ſhewing his Power and Juſtice to ſome, and his Humanity and lenity to others, and not fly out when Things anſwer not the propoſed Ends, but to be armed againſt Diſappointments: For no Ship, though ſteered by a skillful Pilot, will in bad Weather always an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Helm.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152881:23"/>
               <p>Therefore ſince every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey hath its mixtures of good and bad, ſuch Caution ought to be taken, as to connive at what cannot be helped; and ſeem not to ſee, when ſeeing may eclipſe Authority if not exerciſed. It was our Saviour's Advice in the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, That the Tares ſhould not be rooted out, leſt it indamaged the Wheat. Therefore Prudence would rather yield to Fate, and ſhut the Eye and Ear, and bend rather than hazard breaking. The Emblem of <hi>Hercules</hi> his boiſterous managing the Rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der till it broke, may be of uſe to ſhew how the Steerſman may ſpoil the Ship's ſailing for the want of a prudent compliance; and yielding to the circumſtances of times, is the intereſt both of Prince, and People. <hi>Machiavel</hi> tells us, That he who cannot
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152881:23"/>diſſemble knows not how to reign; not that Inſincerity and Hypocriſy is propoſed to be the Standard for the Prince to walk by: But here is intended ſuch a Compliance only as may conſiſt with Honour, and the Peoples Intereſt. There is an honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Condeſcenſion, or yielding, till a fitter Opportunity may offer it ſelf. Princes ſometimes deal with their Subjects as with Children, whoſe weakneſſes are born with, till can be got from them that hurtful Play-thing, they ſo paſſionately cry after.</p>
               <p>Neither ſhould a Prince heap riches to the uneaſe of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; let them ſhear, but not flea their Sheep. Where is the Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to have a beggerly Subjects? As he is the Head of the Body, he ought to have a Regard, that they that repreſent his Authority, do
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152881:24"/>not abuſe it by wounding the Feet; for when they are infeeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led what ſhall ſupport the whole? To prevent which, Covetousneſs is to be diſcouraged; for a Prince is never ſo rich as when he hath his Peoples Hearts, then he needs not queſtion their Purſes. The publick Intereſt is to have none placed in Authority, but ſuch as are deſerving; none ſhould be impowered for favour nor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and when the Prince hath made a fit choice, they ſhould have due incouragements to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Character they bear in the Government; That to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their Grandeur, want may not tempt to take Bribes. But where Virtue is found, there ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Rewards ought to be given according to the Character born; that the Salary and liberality may be ſpurs to Virtue, as their Princes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152881:24"/>favours are incouragements: There is no greater balk to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulators, than to ſee Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes wrong placed on the Heads of the Undeſerving: It is a great incouragement when a Prince ſhall of himſelf make Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the fidelity of his Subjects. To accumulate riches on the Rich, becauſe they are ſuch, is like car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying Water to the <hi>Rhine,</hi> or Gold to <hi>Peru.</hi> But Wiſdom will direct when and where to place Favours proportionable to the Character of the giver and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom the Largeſs is made, that exceptions may not be taken that merit was not recompenſed, and that regard was rather had to Favour, and By-reſpects, than to Deſert; which is not only a ſhame to the giver, but a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to ſuch that have deſerved well. Thus regard is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152881:25"/>to be had both how, and to whom, as well as what, gifts are dispoſed of: For ſuch may libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities be, That the giver may be impoveriſhed, and inſtead of gaining Friends may draw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf Enmity; ſo that even thoſe to whom he hath been liberal to ſave their Stakes may join with Exclaimers, and turn to ridicule that bounty ſhewn them; and that Gift they called liberality, when they received it, ſhall with the common Vogue be ſtyled a profuſe waſting that Treaſure, that might have been preſerved for better purpoſes: Such laviſhings merit rather the Name of Squanderings than Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralities, and in a Prince, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnable as Covetouſneſs: But where liberality is guided with prudence, it redounds to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of both Prince and People.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152881:25"/>
               <p>It is alſo conducible to the publick wellfare that proper In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for council be choſen, ſuch as are wife and faithful, in whom Covetouſneſs doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominate; for where that reigns no good can be expected, as being the Gangrene of the mind, that eateth out Love, Duty, and Honour; therefore ſhould have no more a Place at the Helm than Pride, or Envy: Alſo ſuch ought to be removed as ſhall not from a peak and ſpite, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to an others ſenſe, ſeek out Reaſons to overthrow the beſt advice given, and that becauſe it was not firſt propoſed by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Where there is paſſion there is bandying, and claſhing with Words; and no good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs can be expected from theſe, no more than from thoſe that can not ſee, but with ſuch Spectacles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152881:26"/>as are handed to them at the Board by ſome leading Oracle, without further weighing mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; being wholly Byaſſed by the Opinion they conceive of their Friends Parts, though many times the wiſeſt may not always be in the right. There are alſo ſome that ſee no farther than that Counſel they take upon truſt: Theſe are Ecchos, while others are for fetching Reaſons a far off, in order to the effecting what is propoſed, overlooking more eaſy methods at hand. Theſe know not how to approve any thing, that carrieth not ſome thing of extraordinary in it. But none are more dangerous at the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill Board than theſe that waite to catch at the Prince's Senſe, which they are ſure right or wrong to approve, and make his Thoughts Theirs. Theſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152881:26"/>Flatterers ate not ſufferable in that ſtation where none but the unbiaſſed and ſincere ſhould take Place, and not Sycophants. But there are few Princes whoſe Courts ſwarm not whith theſe; alſo who have not their particular <hi>Achitophels,</hi> yet will not believe they are ſo influenced. But a too over-weeing Opinion of any, how acute ſoever, may befatal. But there are others ſo opinionative of their own Senſe, that they will call a Council only for fomality ſake; though at the ſame time they reſolve to take no Meaſures, but what their own Judgement dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates: Methinks I hear ſuch ſay, with <hi>Xerxes,</hi> I called you that I might not ſeem to follow my own Advice, but it is rather to injoin your obedience than ask Counſel. There are alſo ſome that, with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> after the act
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152881:27"/>is over, are for conſulting, and with him crying out, <hi>Shall 1 draw?</hi> When before he had cut of <hi>Malchus</hi>'s Ear, but none are ſo wiſe but may need advice; <hi>for in the multitude of Counſellers there is ſafety.</hi> For Strength, Riches, and Diligence do not always ſucceed, but it is by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel? and Prudence, that great things are compaſſed. Such Perſons therefore ſhould be made uſe of, as are skilled in the Nature and Diſtemper of the Body Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick; ſuch that like true Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of State may prevent Weeds from taking root, that the publick Peace be not deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſuch as can foreſee State-Diſeaſes by their Symptoms, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they become incurable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than by violent Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Such as are of <hi>Frederic</hi> the Third's Stamp and Approbation,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152881:27"/>who valued thoſe Counſellors moſt, that feared God more than himſelf, who had for end, the Peace and Welfare of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. There is no greater ſafety for a Prince, than to have the Government ſtored with ſuch: Then will he be obeyed, and Peace ſecured; which Peace, how deſirable in it ſelf ſoever it may be; yet it hath attending it Pride, Idleneſs, and Danger: For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a long Peace, Princes and Subjects become ſecure, and Effeminacy, Luſt, and Prodiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity creep in; ſo that even the moſt diſciplined Armies lying ſtill may degenerate, and like the beſt of Horſes pampered; and through want of exerciſe, do looſe their good Qualities. Nothing contributes to ruin a Nation, like luſt, and Pleaſure: When Princes grow potent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152881:28"/>a long Peace, they uſually confide in their Strength, and are tempted to unjuſt Enterpriſes, whoſe ſiniſter Effects fail not to follow ſooner, or later.</p>
               <p>Thus far of Peace, how it may be kept at home againſt the Snakes of their own Boſom, which may prevent War from abroad; yet ſomething may be ſpoken in particular of Peace, as it relates to neighbouring Princes.</p>
               <p>He that will live in Peace with his powerfull Neighbours eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, muſt ſuffer, and not take every thing in the worſt Senſe; but give a grateful Twine to that, which at another Time, and under other Circumſtances, might be called an Injury; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Occaſions of Contentions are cautiouſly to be avoided. Alſo he that will injoy Peace with his Neighbours, muſt always be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152881:28"/>prepared for War: The Hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hog is ever armed againſt his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and there are few. Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals that carry not their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and defenſive weapon about them: As the Ox his Horn, the Bear his Tooth, and the Lion his Paw.</p>
               <p>The prudent Prince will lay up Treaſures againſt the time of need, by ſuch inſenſible Methods, that the People be not oppreſſed, and that occaſion of Diſcontent be not given, and that what ſhall be accumulated, be not waſted by worthleſs Perſons, not miſimployed in fruitleſs, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Contrivances; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is to be had, that all Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities be improved: Looſe no time, was great <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Motto, for delays are dangerous; and as Health, and fair Weather, are ſucceeded by Sickneſs and Storms;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152881:29"/>ſo War ſucceeds Peace. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, of a <hi>time for every Thing;</hi> therefore when Peace gives lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſtore your Magazines with warlike Munitions, that nothing be wanting upon a Surpriſe. It is the Security of a State, always to have an Eye on War, in time of Peace. Keep therefore a Nurſery of Officers of Known perſonal Merit: It is the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Fate of many deſerving, to be laid aſide in Peace, as if never more to be needed; and like Stoves in Summer, are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. But though the Sun ſhines now, yet ſtormy Weather is to be expected, and a regard ought to be had to paſt Deſerts. Alſo an Inſpection ought to be made into the Condition of the ſtanding Forces, that there be no impoſing falſe Muſters: A minute Account ſhould be had of them, as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152881:29"/>alſo of the Stores, and that from time to time aview be made, alſo tryals, and draughts ſhould be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, the better to know what is to be relied on. Thus to preſerve Peace at home and abroad, is to be always ready, and by the help of able Miniſters, Inconveniences may be forſeen, and approaching Dangers prevented, by adminiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering Sutable Remedies anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the preſent Preſſures</p>
               <p>Alſo in peaceable Times to fortify Places, may ſecure the Countrey from Wars at home and abroad; the Reputation of being armed, may prevent both. It is ſtrange how. Men are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of God, yet dare confide in ſinful Men; and by a Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in that kind, give Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to their Countries Ruin. It is the ſimplicity of the Lamb, or Gooſe, that lets them fall into
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152881:30"/>the Wolf and Fox's Paws. The Tortoiſe, diffident of a foreign Shelter, carryeth her Houſe, by Sea and Land, wherein ſhe places her ſafety. It is not in our Days as in <hi>Noah</hi>'s, Ark where Men and Beaſts could ſociably Live and truſt each others; he that never truſts, ſtands on a Guard, and is not eaſily deceived. It is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, That Peace laſts no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than it conſiſts with the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirers Intereſt. There are ſome reſtleſs Spirits that will not be quiet till beaten into good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to the uneaſe of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Subjects. But we muſt not only conſider Peace as a long injoyed Reſt, where there hath been for many Years no Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, but as it immediately ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds War; and ſhew, how after both ſides are wearied by War, the uſual Methods of procuring it, are by the project of Treaties.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152881:30"/>
               <head>Of Treaties, and Negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Peace.</head>
               <p>TO manage which, ſuch proper Inſtruments are to be choſen, ſuch as are well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with their Neighbours Intereſt as well as their own; and alſo with the Genius of thoſe they have to treat with. If it be a powerful State that holds the Rod over you, then a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy of neighbouring Princes is neceſſary to prevent being ſwallowed up a prey to Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There are ſome Miniſters ſo well verſed in politick Strokes, and Conter-pates to know how to turn and wind matters, that they ſhall gain more by Treaties, than Conquerors ſhall effect by Feats of Arms. Many times
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152881:31"/>Peace hath retrieved thoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, which the Sword had loſt: But in Treaties Clergy-men are the worſt choice; who, like evil Spirits, ought to be conjured out of the circle of Negotiations, and from having a ſhare in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the Civil Government, leſt they confound all meaſures of Peace: For they make the worſt Stateſmen, who though they have the Voices of Doves, and have nothing leſs than Peace in their Mouths; yet they bear Stings in their Tails; they come with Olive-branches in their Beaks, but Experience hath taught that wherever they come to ſit at the Helm, they occaſion Diſcord and Confuſion.</p>
               <p>Many times to ſerve a turn, Sham Treaties are ſet on Foot to gain time, where much is offered, though little intended more than deluſory Amuſements to compaſs
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152881:31"/>By-ends; of theſe blinds, the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Plenipotentiary is watchful, leſt inſtead of a Cordial, he meet with a purgative Potion. All State-engines ought to be conſidered, as ſo many Buyers of Wares, who to compaſs their deſired Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, ſeldom ſpeak as they think; but this our Stateſman, being acquainted with the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of each Power, and the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks by which they ſteer their courſe, will know how to turn the Mill that way, that may beſt anſwer that Quarter the Wind ſits in. Leſſer Potentates ſhould Act with potent Neighbours circumſpectly; eſpecially when they have to do with ſuch whoſe Maxims are, That their Princes ought not to be Slaves to their Word; and that Truth and Sincerity are but vulgar Vertues: It is thoſe that are to be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, let their manner of acting
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152881:32"/>appear never ſo frank and oepn: For ſuch can ſtteer their courſe by all Winds, and will ſcruple at no means, how illegitimate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to compaſs their Deſigns of cruſhing others, and clothing themſelves with their Dominions. Theſe are they, whoſe Ambition hath no Bounds, but what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity compels them too; againſt whom, as Common Enemies to Property, all adjacent Potentates ſhould arm and unite, to ſupport each others Intereſt. Nothing can be more uneaſy, than when a Prince, or State, is placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Emulators for Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; to carry even betwixt them, and to give jealouſy to neither, is a hard Game to play; and thoſe ſo concerned run a Hazard of being ground in pieces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſuch Rocks. It is therefore requiſite to be always in good
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152881:32"/>Intelligence with thoſe they may have occaſion to uſe as Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, or Mediators, that the power of over-growing Greatneſs may be balanced; that they may not, after the example of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Fiſhes, devour the leſſer fry of States, that lie in their way; which, if ſuffered, may be of ill conſequence to ſuch, as ſtand by as Spectators; leſt their turn be next to put on that Yoke they ſuffer their Neighbours to be yoked with. It is ſurely the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt of Princes, to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of Incroachers and Incro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achments; being evil Preſidents that in time may affect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as well as their Neighbours, who by ſtopping that current they ſerve themſelves. If two Powers, Emulators for Empire, ſhould jar and juſtle each other; then it is the common Intereſt to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152881:33"/>let them claſh and contend to their weakening, provided ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spectators lay not a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for future Breaches. Such ſurely was the reſerved Policy of <hi>Innocent</hi> X. when deſired to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate a Peace betwixt two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders for Empire, gave Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Panzirolo</hi> to remark out of his Window, two Porters fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whom he would not ſuffer to be parted till they thought fit to leave off themſelves; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Thus will the contending Princes do, when wearied, they will leave off without a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the many Cautions to thoſe that treat, ſomething might be ſaid of the Intereſt of ſuch leſſer States as have conteſts with Neighbours of their own Rank, who ought to avoid jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, ſo as their Differences
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152881:33"/>ariſe not to an open Rupture. Some proper Mediator therefore ought to be found, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate Differences; ſo as the Honour of each may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: For if the Conteſt ariſe to Hoſtility, it may prove of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal conſequence to both, and give occaſion for a predominant Power to profit by the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and annex them both to his Dominions; and ſerve them as the Bird of prey in the Fable did the Frog and Mouſe, who ſeized of both. Neither ſhould leſſer States call a ſuperior to be an Aſſiſtant, leaſt he ſerve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and not the Proprietor; of which Hiſtory hath on Record various Examples, of thoſe that made ill uſe of ſuch Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and inſtead of ſerving the Intereſt of thoſe that called them as Aſſiſtants, they made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152881:34"/>Maſters. Therefore it is beſt to avoid all Occaſions of difference, and not be obſtinate to wreak a Spite, but to accept of ſuch Terms as may be obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſuffer the loſs of a part rather than expoſe the whole.</p>
               <p>But there are ſometimes ſuch Peaces propoſed, that an open War is more deſirable, and leſs to be feared. Neither can Peace founded on unjuſt Conditions be long-lived; which are like ill cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wounds that feſter and prove the Patients greater Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>Neither is a new reconciled Enemy to be truſted, eſpecially if he hath been the Aggreſſor; for ſuch ſeldom pardon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries they have done themſelves; becauſe they believe they can not be forgiven. Let the Fox cover himſelf never ſo artificially with a Lamb's Skin, yet the wary
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152881:34"/>will dread him. Neither let any Inducement charm the Sword into its Scabbard, nor perſwade to a too early disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Forces: That Shepherd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Cenſure, that will hearken to the Wolf to ſend away his Dogs.</p>
               <p>Having ſaid ſomething of Peace at Home, and of preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it by neceſſary Cautions with neighbouring Potentates, and of ſecurity by Treaties, the deſired hope; and though occaſionally ſomething hath been hinted at about making Leagues, yet it may be neceſſary to make further ſome addition on the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:152881:35"/>
               <head>Of Leagues.</head>
               <p>ALthough Alliances are good yet thoſe are to be pitied that ſtand in need of them; and ſhould conſider with whom Leagues Offenſive, and Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive are made. Unequal Powers in affinity may be of ill Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; for the weaker Lies at the mercy of the ſtronger, and is tempted to ſeek redreſs from another Power capable to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect him: For Confederates have divers Faces; it is their Tails only that are twiſted together. When the Sheep become the Lions Aſſociates, their Skins uſually pay for it; for between Unequals there can be no equal Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy. The Great have great Deſigns, the Leſſer ſuch as are
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152881:35"/>ſutable to their different Stations; one gives, the other takes. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity makes the unwilling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly condeſcending, and as with the dividing the Spoil got in hunting, in a common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy of the Beaſts, the Lion will claim ſo many Parts and pretended Rights, that he will leave his Companions to ſtand by as Spectators, ſilently to diſpenſe with their Rights, and ſuffer their irremediable Loſſes, without diſcovering the leaſt Reſentment. For what can be alledged, when the Character of a King, Merit and Proweſs is pleaded, and after that of his Will not to be controlled? What can his modeſt Companions do leſs than make a Vertue of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and ſuffer their Rights to be diſpoſed of, how unjuſtly ſoever Raviſhed from them? Thus the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152881:36"/>powerful profits to the loſs of the weaker Competitor. This comes by being tyed to the Intereſt of a Potent Allye; who inſtead of a Helper finds a Maſter, ſuch will know no Partners. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is of ill conſequence for leſſer Powers to be reduced to joyn with the Stronger; though it may ſut a preſent occaſion. Alliances with ſuch Confederates contribute to Augment that Power, that when time ſerves, may be made uſe of, to inſlave themſelves: For when ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates have ſecured their ends, what can they expect more than that Fate, that <hi>Polyphemus</hi> gave <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi> of being Devoured the laſt?</p>
               <p>Another Inconveniency an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to leſſer Powers, when im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked in League with a more powerful, is that, whenever
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152881:36"/>the ſame greatneſs comes to juſtle, and contend as Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor with another of equal might; then the leſſer by Virtue of the Confederacy, is expoſed to all the Streights and Deſolations, that attend Hoſtilities. And if the formidable Power ſuffers, and bends under the Weight of the Adverſaries Arms, what leſs can be expected, than to be Sunk, and Buried in his Ruins? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a prudent Diffidence is to be had of all Compacts, wherein Safety is Expoſed. It is true, that to prevent foreſeen Evils, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity doth ſometimes oblige to Imbrace for Allye a more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Party; and when a Prince's Word is once Ingaged; it is confeſſed, That it is very Diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous, not to ſay worſe, to break Covenants Solemnly Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulated; but that is not here the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152881:37"/>Queſtion: For as they can not be juſtified, ſo ſhall I not wholly Condemn the Breaking thoſe Leagues, which incroaching Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates have Neceſſitated: For there may be ſuch Reaſons drawn from Self-preſervation, and the hard Termsimpoſed, that though the breach of Oaths can not be juſtified; yet they may admit of a moſt favourable Conſtruction: For Oppreſſion and neceſſity may extort ſuch Terms, that the Prince would Sin againſt his Perſon and Subjects, ſhould he inviolably keep them, ſo that though the making them at firſt was an evil; yet the breaking of them ſeems a leſs, than that of their keeping: So that although the breaking ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Oaths may not be Scrupled; yet the making any Illegitimate ones is to be Condemned; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152881:37"/>that which with Honour and Juſtice can not be Maintained.</p>
               <p>It may be obſervable, That thoſe with whom Leagues are made, ought to be ſuch, that we may be aſſured they are Friends, that in diſtreſs will be a recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Help, and not be Biaſſed by Fear or Lucre. A true Friend, like Blood, ſprings forth as ſoon as the Wound is made. It is obſerved, That Swine, when they hear their Follows cry, will fly to their aſſiſtance in Danger: Therefore the Lion would make no League but with that Herd, that in Neceſſity is ſo faithful. Leagues are never ſo likely to be Religiouſly obſerved, as when made with ſuch, as are not too much ſuperiour in Power; they are nice Things, and though a Remedy againſt Danger; yet themſelves are a Danger, though
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152881:38"/>preſent Circumſtances ſometimes call for them. In ſuch Junctures, the Prince is to arm himſelf with Caution, that he repent not, and ſeek to break Compacts ſo ſolemnly exchanged. But God ought to be conſulted; for if he ties not the knot, the bond of Peace will ſoon be unlooſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of War.</head>
               <p>AS Peace vaniſhes, ſo War takes Place, each followeth the Heels of the other; as the one ſets, the other overſpreads the Horizon; and as Darkneſs ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds Light, ſo War ſucceeds Peace.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the many infinite per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections God diſcovered of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Man, that of Immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152881:38"/>is only peculiar to the Deity; ſince no created Beings, how excellent ſoever in their Nature, but were made liable to change, and left to a poſſibility of falling from that State in which they were placed. Thus <hi>Lucifer</hi> from a glorious Angel became a Devil; it is matter of Aſtoniſhment, That in Heaven, where he was placed in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Orb of Happineſs and Peace; that he could not be content, but muſt rebell againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. It is matter of Wonder, That even Heaven, where the God of Peace reigns, ſhould not be exempt from Rebellion, and ſince the Fall, it ſeems, as if Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition were the very Eſſence of all created Beings. How are the Elements in Hoſtility? How doth the Earth quake? The Sea roar? the Air thunder, and the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152881:39"/>Brutes wage War againſt each other? The Greater devouring the Leſſer. And no wonder, That Men are drawn in, having ſuch Prompters as the Devil, and their own perverſe Natures, that they can not without jarring, live in neither City, nor Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. How early did this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhew it ſelf? For, even in the Womb, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> ſtruggled for Maſtery, and when born, what fewds were there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two Twins in their Father's Family? That, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing, they were forced to be ſeparated, till lenghth of Time had worn out their Animoſities. Alſo a Father and Son, <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abſalon;</hi> a Kingdom could not contain them, but one muſt Rival the other for Empire: And which is more, <hi>Cain</hi> and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152881:39"/>
                  <hi>Abel,</hi> though they had the World betwixt them; yet was their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord Fatal. Thus Satan as from the beginning, ſo to this Day, he perſiſts in fomenting Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; ſetting Man againſt Man, Family againſt Family, and Nation againſt Nation; putting all into Confuſion by Broils and Wars; through which Riches are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed for Poverty, and Sorrows are introduced in lieu of thoſe Delights that accompany Peace; who as it is the Health of a State, and a Nouriſher and Incourager of Arts; ſo is War its Sickneſs, and the Diſcouragement of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuities: For in the midſt of Noiſe and Hurry, none can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſutable returns of Vertue, where Diſſoluteneſs ſeems to be let looſe, to make way for Pride, Strife and Contentions, and where every one labours to make
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152881:40"/>his Neighbour his Prey. Thus where War is, there Miſery over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flows, like an impetuous Torrent, carrying away even to the very marks of Proſperity that Peace had formerly left its Inhabitants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>There are two kinds of War, <hi>viz.</hi> Civil, and Foreign.</head>
               <p>CIVIL War is uſually the Daughter of a bigotted Zeal for a publick Good, and feigned Liberty and Property; it is from inteſtine Broils that proceeds Irreverence and Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and through the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetneſs of Nature and manners juſtice, Majeſty and Laws are trodden under Foot to make way for Spoil, and ſetting up ſome private Intereſt; or to wreak
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152881:40"/>ſome conceived ſpite: Such are like thoſe Fiſhers that find advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by caſting their Nets in troubled Waters. Inteſtine Heats, if not timely quenched, may prove the Deſtruction of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, and are worſe than foreign Wars. And as Diſeaſes within the Body, are more to be feared than remoter Griefs; ſo Civil War is attended with more ſiniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Effects, than that from Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abroad; for where the Bowels of a State are diſaffected, there the Father is againſt his Son, and every Man's Sword againſt his Fellow; and as a Houſe divided cannot ſtand; ſo the Ruin of that State may be expected, where one Member wounds the other, to the Hurt of the Whole. Theſe Wars, called Civil, are the moſt Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil; for then is laid aſide all
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152881:41"/>reſpect and conſideration, with reference to Affinity, Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity or Friendſhip; for Friend knows not his Friend, nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation Relation, neither doth the Son know his Father, nor Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant his Maſter, no more than the Subject knows his Prince. Thus States and Common-wealths have their Diſeaſes as well as Men. It is the wiſe Phyſician's part, to find out its Cauſe; for when known, the Maladie is half cured: And as Purging and Bleeding is requiſite to full Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, where Bloud abounds, and ill Humours are grown to a ferment; ſo Phlebotomy in a State, is neceſſary when Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents are riſen up, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Diſeaſe of the Place, ſo as to affect the Body Politick. Let the Evil proceed from what cauſe ſoever, it matters not; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neither
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152881:41"/>is it material from what quarter the Wind Blows, if it indangers the Houſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the Diſcord proceed from what Cauſe or Perſons ſoever; whether from a foreign deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power or from Poverty, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion or Idleneſs, or from the popularity of ſome particular indeared One to the People, as <hi>Abſalom</hi> was in his time; all which being ſo many Rock's or Shelves, the Pilot, who ſits at the Helm, ought to ſteer his Ship ſo as to avoid the threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Danger; and though he hath formerly eſcaped, yet is he not to reſt ſecure; for though every Vapour may not turn to a Storm, yet it is good that the Ship's Tack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling be ready to weather the Tempeſt, that ſhe may be ſafely ſteered into the Harbour of Peace.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:152881:42"/>
               <p>Civil War ordinarily hath theſe following Pretences; as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which is of great weight to influence a bigotted Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, an invaſion of Properties, which annexed to the former, will go a great way to unhinge all. Thus if Laws be broken, Privileges infringed, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects oppreſſed, whether by Taxes, or by the Irregularity of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. Alſo when Perſons of no merit are impowered, any Thing will ſerve malecontents to exclaim and take occaſion to gratify their Spite; though the ſecret Cauſe of their Inveterateneſs proceeds from their not being preferred, and that their imaginary Merit is not anſwered: But whatever the inducements may be, they are but a wild ſort of Executors of Juſtice, who taking pet at the World, will chuſe rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152881:42"/>themſelves on themſelves, than not gratify their Humour; but theſe hereby involve alſo the ignorant Commonalty, that like Tinder are ſubject to take Fire; ſuch, rather than ſit ſtill, under thoſe Bounds that Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath preſcribed them, will run the hazard of their own Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Alſo Princes Auſterity to their Subjects may be a means to bring on themſelves, as well as People, many Evils. The ſame may be ſaid of private Fewds in great Families, that they are the Forerunners of Tumults in a State; eſpecially when they ariſe to that height, as to forme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into diſorderly Aſſemblies, from ſuch Sparks are often kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Civil Diſſenſions. Likewiſe want of Bread may be an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for nothing makes more
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152881:43"/>deſperate than a Dearth, and the more, if there be no proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of a Remedy.</p>
               <p>The Remedies of Civil War may in ſome meaſure be effected; when its Cauſes are known, then ſutable ways may be found to appeaſe the incenſed Ones. If the imperious Humour of the Prince be occaſion, then let him change his Conduct; for ſuch may be the churliſh Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a Maſter, that his Dogs may be ſo incenſed, as to ſhew their Teeth, and Snarl, though they may not always Bite: Soft Words, and a debonaire Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, coſt nothing. Had <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam</hi> practiſed this Rule, he had not loſt Ten Tribes; but if any publick Miniſters abuſe the Power they are intruſted with, then let them be removed, and made, publick Examples to deter
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152881:43"/>others. Doth penury, and want of Bread, cauſe Exclaimers, and Hurricanes are thereby raiſed amongſt the People? Then let Monopoliſers of Proviſions be obliged to bring forth their Stores, and Sell at a regulated Price; for private Intereſt ſhould give way to the publick Good. In order to which let Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, Mechanicks, and Merchants be incouraged; and ſuffer not Money to lodge in a few Hands, but find ways to make it Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, leſt it be ſaid, That Want reigns where Riches abound.</p>
               <p>Common-wealths are compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of two ſorts of People, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Commonalty, under which general Heads are ſeveral Claſſes of Men. The latter is a great Body, ſlow of Motion; therefore as a ſpur to quicken them, the Nobility is neceſſary;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152881:44"/>not only to excite, but alſo to ſteer them in their right Biaſs, for the Example of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty doth wonderfully influence thoſe more heavy Maſſes, and by a ſort of Sympathy infuſes in them new Spirits, and gives Courage to undertake, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute generous Enterpriſes: For the Nobility wanting Numbers can not effect, what neceſſity might require from more nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Bodies. Thus Nature hath wiſely ordered each degree of Men to be neceſſary to the other, that reciprocally they might be the ſtay and ſupport of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Politick, without which Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it could not ſubſiſt.</p>
               <p>It is the Wiſdom of thoſe that ſit at the Helm to uſe means to keep up that noble Heat, with which the Multitude may be inſpired, and not ſuffer their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152881:44"/>laudable Reſolutions to cool; in order to which, hopes of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Recompences are the great Engines of uſe on all occaſions: For let Hopes dye, and you may bid farewell to Succeſſes, and conclude that both will ſink to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; for Hope is the life of Enterpriſes, it ſets all Wheels on going, even from the crowned Head to the Dunghill; each have their Aims and Ends with which they flatter themſelves into an imaginary Happineſs, though they never live to ſee it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed.</p>
               <p>But as hath been before hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on an other occaſion, That as all humane Bodies are ſubject to vicious Humours, ſo the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Politick hath its Diſeaſes and Tumors, which ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed by a timely prevention: For amongſt the Nobility, of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152881:45"/>whom more reaſonably might be expected fidelity from their Birth and Education, are found thoſe that are drawn away, though they poſſeſs the Prince's Favour, or at leaſt injoy his Preſence, to which by their Quality they are intitled unto, that one would think might be ſufficient to ſteer them in the right way. But unhappy for them, and alſo for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where ſuch Diſorders hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, for theſe prove the moſt dangerous Tools of Miſchief, and the more, in that their Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation hath given them acquired Qualifications by which they are capacitated to be more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally good, or evil Inſtruments: But let the Cauſe of Diſcontent be what it will however juſtifya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the prepoſſeſſed Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſuch diſaffected Ones,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152881:45"/>that is not here the ſubject, but to ſhew how to quench, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh thoſe Fire-brands, and Ring-leaders to miſchief.</p>
               <p>The firſt Remedy therefore propoſed is, That the diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Party by fair means be drawn to their Duty and Allegiance, from a true apprehenſion of their own Intereſt, with that of their Countreys; in order to which, Reaſons may be taken with reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to the one, and the other, and that by ſome proper In ſtrument ſuch honourable Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction might be propoſed as may conſiſt with the Prince's Character of Soveraign, when he treats with his Subjects.</p>
               <p>But if fair Means fail, and that the Offenders are inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then ecclipſe that ſuppoſed Merit, by which the Head of the Faction is boyed up in the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar's
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152881:46"/>Opinion: To promote which, inſinuate Fears and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, that the fervor with which the Tumult is excited to Sedition, may be cooled; to compaſs which, let the Prince have in his Eye ſuch, whoſe known deſert hath not made them the Subject of the Peoples envie; ſuch, whoſe Integrity and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs, annexed with their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in military Affairs, may carry on awful fear, and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for their Perſon.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>David</hi>'s Policy may be of uſe, by ſending a <hi>Huſhai</hi> to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine their <hi>Achitophels,</hi> that by Intelligence, and a Diffidence inſinuated, the Enemy may be weakened, and divided into Factions; on ſuch Occaſions not only Policy, but Money may be a proper Bait: For what can not Gold effect? What hath
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152881:46"/>it not done in ſuch Caſes? It is as Oil to the Wheel, that makes all Things Eaſy; opens Cloſet-doors, diſcloſes Secrets, impoſes Silence, or makes the Prieſts Mouth Speak; it inflames Zeal, creates Friends, and makes thoſe that were Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſuch, as they would ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice all to carry on that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, which before was their Averſion: So wonderfull is the operation of this Metal, that it blinds the Eyes of the Seeing, and opens thoſe that before could not diſcern; and makes the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulteſt Enterpriſes eaſy by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving all Obſtacles.</p>
               <p>But when all Means fail, and that ſuppreſſing Sedition is the Queſtion, then let a Door timely be opened to thoſe that by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſhall come in, and take hold of Pardon; which, when propoſed, ought moſt Religiouſly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152881:47"/>to be obſerved: Offenders are not to be abandoned to Deſpair; that makes thoſe the inveterateſt Enemies, which, by prudent Management, might have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come uſefull Friends. Let not <hi>Machiavel's</hi> Aſſertion be counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, That to the end Deſigns may not be abortive, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be perfectly Wicked: But ſince Princes and Subjects are Mortal, why ſhould their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions be immortal? Neither is it good to penetrate too far into the Nature of Offences, eſpecially when the Sore is ſpreading. But as Corruptions increaſe, and ways found to evade the Law, ſo ſhould Juſtice be awakened to the exſtinguiſhing of growing Evils.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:152881:47"/>
               <head>Of Foreign War.</head>
               <p>FOreign War is a leſs Evil, and a generouſer Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than the Civil, which may be reduced to that of Offenſive, and Defenſive.</p>
               <p>The Offenſive is either Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, or Juſt. The occaſions taken for an Unjuſt War are ſometimes ſo trivial, as may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be lamented than inquired into, and ſo with reaſon is called Offenſive.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, Offenſive War.</head>
               <p>THe Opinion, that Right conſiſts in that we are ſtronger than our Neighbours,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152881:48"/>or that God takes the ſtrongeſt Part, is a Tenent to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: For he is a Supporter of juſtice, and the giver of Victory; which may be reaſonablier ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, when Juſtice and Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty compel to take Arms for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge. Having Self-preſervation, and Peace for End, ſucceſs may better be expected; but they have reaſon to be jealous of their good Fortune, when Ambition and Covetouſneſs ſet them on work.</p>
               <p>This Unjuſt, Offenſive War is the legitimate off-ſpring of Pride and Ambition, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by ſuch who are Scourges in God's Hands by whoſe means Countries are depopulated, and Devaſtations made. Such are Beaſoms in God's Hands, with which he ſweeps Nations. This ſort of War is, in its Nature,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152881:48"/>offenſive to Mankind, whoſe Undertaker ſeems to deſign the Deſtruction of his Species.</p>
               <p>This is the moſt unnatural of Enterpriſes, and looks as if Men had forgot they were Men, and that they had diveſted themſelves of their Underſtanding and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; and were become more cruel, each to other, than irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Brutes are to thoſe of their own Sort, who wage not War, one kind againſt thoſe of the ſame. The Lion ordinarily tears not the Lion, nor the Tiger and Wolf thoſe of their kind; they aſſemble not in Herds, and form not deſtructive Projects by ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering Parties againſt Parties. Alſo our Lord gives us to believe, That though the Devils are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Mankind, yet that they are not divided amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152881:49"/>for if ſo, their Kingdom could not ſtand.</p>
               <p>Is it not Folly and Frenzie to ſeek Occaſions to be a Plague to the Age, and an Inſtrument of torment to others? To effect which, they will run through all Hazards by Sea and Land, and for Uncertainties court Death and Deſtruction; and with ſo much fierceneſs imbark others with themſelves, to endeavour the Ruin of thoſe they neither hate, nor know: As it is with every hired Souldier that invades the Perſons and Properties of ſuch who never gave him offenſe. Thus theſe mercenary Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons contribute, as far as in them lies, to the promoting the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and ſad Effects of ſuch Debordements, even to which themſelves they bear their ſhare. Thoſe mercenary Ones, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152881:49"/>not the Juſtice of a Cauſe, but fight for the empty Name of being Valourous, and the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable recompences intailed on them, rather deſerve to be ſtyled Mad-men, who give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up a Prey to the Sword, and hazard for trifles their All to the Mercy of incenſed Ones; who will have no conſideration to reduce ſuch, either to their firſt Nothing, or to render them uſeleſs by loſs of Members, which is more deplorable than Death it ſelf: And this to ſerve the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an ambitious One in an unjuſt Cauſe; and perhaps ſuch an one, who neither knows, nor cares, for their Perſons, farther than to obtain his End; nor would Scruple, when occaſion offered, to ſerve himſelf of their dead Bodies, as a Pedeſtal to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152881:50"/>heighten his Stature to take the farther view.</p>
               <p>But when God, and Reaſon, calls for the Defence of their Countrey, Prince, and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, then to dye, or ſuffer, in ſuch a cauſe, is honourable, and a Duty incumbent on the Subject. It is deplorable, the ſad Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may be made of the Effects incident to Wars; which in themſelves are ſufficient to deter the Promoters of unjuſt Ones. The hardening themſelves againſt ſuch Conſiderations are Aggravations of their Crimes; for from that time they are launched from the Shore of Peace, they alſo involve themſelves, and others, into a Sea of Troubles, with whoſe angry Waves they wreſtle, and are toſſed, and hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by the Wind of Fortune in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Gulph of Miſery; which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152881:50"/>hath a Mouth wide like Hell, and refuſes no Comers, but Preyes moſtly on the Valiant, and ſuch as are fitteſt for noble Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: The moſt robuſt and daring, and thoſe liklieſt to live, are more immediately its Objects; and like the Lion, the King of Beaſts, diſdains a mean Prey, and as he ſpares none, but cruſhes all that come under his Paws. So this King of Terrours, when ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Triumph on his Chariot of War, then the impotent, the baſe, the Coward, are not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately the Object of his lure, as the bold and daring, ſuch as with courage can look Death in the Face; thus like the generous Hawk, he takes his flight on the nobleſt Quarry.</p>
               <p>But ſuch is the miſery inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to Man, that ſometimes God ſuffers in an Age a Scourge
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152881:51"/>to ariſe, who being given up to a boundleſs Ambition, is unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable even to the raviſhing his Neighbour's Properties; which after he calls his, and that for no juſter reaſon than that ſuch was his pleaſure; and after an illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Poſſeſſion, claims a right to adjacent Places by virtue of their Reunion. Thus ſome Mens deſires are boundleſs like the Ocean, and as the Grave are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſatisfied; for preſuming on their Power and Strength, they inſult their Neighbours. But where is the generoſity: To ſeek occaſions of Conteſt where none is given, and that on frivolous, and often on no pretext ſurpriſe the diſarmed, or at leaſt upon ſuch a diſarity of Force as makes them no proper Objects for a generous Undertaker? But ſuch run the Hazard of this Cenſure,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152881:51"/>That as the leſſer Hectors, where, they have an advantage, will, on every ſlight Occaſion, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and draw; and wanting matter for Conteſt, will rake it out of nothing. Thus the greater to ſerve their turn wage War, and tell the reaſon after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. But ſo abſtruſe are the Inducements for their irregular Proceedings, that even <hi>Oedipus</hi> himſelf, how clear-ſighted ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, had he been living, could not have diſcovered whence, nor why were ſuch Hoſtilities; yet ſuch are the Paraſitical Humours of many, that after a ſucceſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, they will ſing the Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums of Praiſes of thoſe whom they know have diſhonoured God, and done the Devil's Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</p>
               <p>Thus unwarrantable Actions take a new Name, and bury that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152881:52"/>of Uſurpation in the Bowels of Victory, that it ſeems as if Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and Right were indiſſolvably knit together. Thus the Glory of overcoming, or being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, denominates the Enterpriſe good or evil; and, accordnig to the common acceptation of things, Fame Ecchoes forth Praiſe or Diſpraiſe. Thus little Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries are called Thefts, while thoſe great ones of Principalities and Countries are ſtyled Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and Heroick Actions. Thus Uſurpation changes its Name, and the Uſurper is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the lawful Prince; whoſe fortunate Succeſs is adored by the gazing World, while the Sufferer is deſpiſed and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Thus the ſmall Fry in the Seas is made the prey to greater Fiſhes, and the leſſer Fowl to Birds of prey. Thus powerful
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152881:52"/>Princes imboldened by their ſtrength like Wolves, ſeiſe on their Neighbours Flocks, and hug themſelves with this impious Maxim, That wicked Enterpriſes change their Nature with their Names, and become Vertues, when attended with Succeſs. Thus is he exalted to pride him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf whoſe Bloud boiling in a high Ferment of Glory, is imboldened to farther Inſolencies though he runs the hazard of Eternal Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance; for the all-powerful is not tied to Means, but with the Uſurper's own Weapons, whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Deſtroy his Neighbours, he may thereby himſelf be made a Victim, and the meaſure he meated to others, may be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated on him.</p>
               <p>But what can we expect, when the Reflections of a Superiour Vengeance will not take Place,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152881:53"/>that any more inferiour Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration ſhould be available? Or that he ſhould be induced to moderation, from any Reaſon drawn from his Honour, that is eclipſed by oppreſſing ſuch who have not might to Subſiſt, but under the ſhelter of a more Auſpicious Wing. But it is not thus amongſt irrational Animals; for the generous Lion diſdains to make the Mouſe his prey; nor will the Eagle catch Flies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Juſt Offenſive War.</head>
               <p>IT may be preſumed that none will undertake ſuch Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, unleſs well-provided with neceſſary Requiſites; it concerns not leſs ſuch who have a legal Reaſon to begin a Juſt Offenſive
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152881:53"/>War, than thoſe who want that Title to juſtify their Actions, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince Honour, Reaſon, and Juſtice alarm them to action.</p>
               <p>It may be with juſtice deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated Offenſive, yet not from the ſame Reaſon that the Unjuſt War is ſo called; for in this War Juſtice is implied, and is a Right that the Prince doth himſelf, and his People, who is ſuppoſed to be the Sufferer of wrong, either from omiſſion of right expected, or from a Commiſſion of wrong done. Thus, though cauſe be given for a Juſt Offenſive War, yet before imbarking therein, let the reaſons of the undertaking be ſcrutinouſly looked into, and not take fire at every alarm, though there may be Amuſements, and that Returns of juſt Demands may be dilatory and deluſory, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152881:54"/>Incroachments may be made on various Pretences, and that Words in Treaties may be wreſted: Alſo ſuch may Circumſtances of Time and Place be, as to furniſh mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for Conteſt; all which the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prince will not immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely reſent, and take the alarm at every diſguſt, but rather by moderation Calm Heats, uſing means to reconcile Miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, giving right Ideas of Things by placing matters indiſpute in their true Light; for the events of War are like caſts at Hazard, where the Dice com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly runs contrary to expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which Fate hath a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhare than Reaſon: Though the Enterpriſe may be plauſible, and eaſy at firſt Undertaking, yet there will be found Difficulties, and the End uncertain, if not Fatal; and oftentimes the Victor
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152881:54"/>hath occaſion to ſay with <hi>Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus,</hi> when he had vanquiſhed the <hi>Roman</hi> Forces, to thoſe that congratulated his Succeſs, That their Tranſports of Joy ought to be moderated by Silence, ſince ſuch another Victory would have undone him. Thus it may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that the Conquerour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits not by his Conqueſt: Thoſe are ſurely moſt unhappy Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, where neither Party can promiſe themſelves to profit by their Enterpriſes; but that there is an indubitable neceſſity, that both muſt be Loſers; as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens in all warlike Undertakings; there being never Tears wanting in the greateſt Solemnities of Triumphs. The Armour is ſoon put on, the City is ſoon in a Flame, but the Remedies of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration are not eaſily effected; and Fortune, who is inconſtant,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152881:55"/>is never ſo eminently ſuch, as in her diſpenſing her Laurels. Princes may be ſaid to be like Fiſhers, who angle for a Prize, though they uſe the golden Hook, yet ſometimes they not only miſs the Prey, but even Bait-hook, and all are often loſt; ſo that though the Gainer of the Bait hath dearly purchaſed the ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that Morſel, yet hath the Angler little Cauſe of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph; and many times gazing Spectators have ſeen their Heads crowned with unexpected Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies and Honour, whom they expected ſhould have been made Victims. It is very diſingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous not to ſay worſe, on every ſlight Occaſion, to place the welfare of the Subject on the Sword's Point. But ſome, like Gameſters, that have ſo itching an humour for Play, that rather
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152881:55"/>than ſtand out, will hazard all.</p>
               <p>It is not prudent, at all Times, to begin a juſt War, eſpecially when the Evil that accrues by it, is greater than the Good that can be expected from a reaſonable Compliance. Let ſoft and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing means be uſed with ſuch honourable Condeſcenſions, as may conſiſt with the Prince's Character. But if Neceſſity compels, and that Reaſon and Juſtice countenance his Cauſe, then let Diligence and Vigilancy be awakened, to proſecute ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually what ſhall be begun. For ſince nothing leſs than Fire and Sword will be available, uſe them as the laſt Remedy to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that Peace, which fair means could not effect. Which having firſt eſſayed may give occaſion with more reaſon to expect a a proſperous Succeſs. By which
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152881:56"/>we ſee how the uſe of Arms is neceſſary, and that the Military Profeſſion ought to be honoured, and incouraged; but however laudable it is in itſelf, yet ſuch ill uſe hath been made of it, as to give occaſion for the unthink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Multitude to exclaim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, as one of the Plagues of Mankind, and as a Science hatched in Hell for the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Humane Society. But as the beſt of Food turns to ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours when it lights upon a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and a diſaffected Stomack: So the military Profeſſion may be miſuſed; and as skill and Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons in the Hands of Robbers are hurtful and deſtructive, but commendable, when lodged with the honeſt Traveller, who imploys them to defend his Perſon, and Effects.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:152881:56"/>
               <p>Thus the Military Art, and its Profeſſors, recommend themſelves to the World as the ſtay of Lives, Laws, Liberties and Properties. There is no Profeſſion ſo honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as the Military, nor more uſeful in its Place, when mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by a prudent Conduct. It is noble in its Cauſe when legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, as alſo in its Execution, by which its Profeſſors are innobled, and capacitated for the higheſt Honours; ſo that thereby they are adorned with Purples, and many times their Merit recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced with Crowns and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Even from private Centinels ſome have raiſed themſelves to the higheſt pitch of Preferment, and by their Vertue and Proweſs have commanded ſuch, whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore themſelves have obeyed. No Characters of Men whatſoever, deſerve more from the Hands of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152881:57"/>their Prince, not only in reſpect of their preſent Uſe, but alſo in regard of the Antiquity of their Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. For we read of Hoſtilities before Learning had poliſhed, refined, and dignified Men; for after the Perſon of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, they are the nobleſt, and the more in this reſpect, That the Prince prides himſelf in the glorious Epithet of being ſtiled a Souldier; and it is the Prince's peculiar Province, to innoble and recompence Valour, by Military Honours. Alſo in many reſpects, they exceed the learned Heads, however crowned with Bays: For they are not only the preſervers of Laws and Religion, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of Perſons and Properties; but that Countrey, where the Military Art is incouraged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Nurſery of all Sciences, and under their Wing, Trade Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152881:57"/>and Riches increaſe, to the Honour and Strength of that State and Government, where that Profeſſion is kept on Foot; but where it lies dormant, a Door is opened to the firſt Ambititious One, that ſhall find himſelf at leiſure to inſult their Security.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Defenſive War.</head>
               <p>HItherto War hath been our Subject, ſo far as regards the offenſive Part, whether Juſt, or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; in the latter the Innocent is aſſaulted, and reduced to defend himſelf. It is time now to give ſome Hints, with reference to the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Part of War, where Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation calls for the Vindication of invaded Rights of the Innocents, who are therein paſſive, and by an impulſe of Fate hurried on to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152881:58"/>themſelves; like thoſe harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Clients, who fly to the Law for refuge from their litigious, vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Neighbours. It is from this verbal War, that the more bloudy one, made by Fire and Sword, may have derived its Name; and as a Metaphor, drawn from defending the Cauſe, hath taken its name of a Defenſive War, when the aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is neceſſitated to arm in his own Defence againſt the Aggreſſor.</p>
               <p>It is Natural to all ſublunary Creatures, animated with Life, to ſeek their Preſervation; and God hath imprinted it in the very Nature of irrational Animals to preſerve themſelves from an invading Foe, and for that end hath furniſhed each with ſutable Weapons: Some have their Horns, ſome are taught the uſe of the Heel, others have their Teeth and Claws for Weapons; even the very Reptiles and Inſects
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152881:58"/>have their Stings, which they uſe when provoked.</p>
               <p>Since Self-defence is a Dictate of Nature amongſt irrational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; ſo it is in Man, even the Laws of Nations will that Force be repelled by Force: Yet ſome are of Opinion, That Self-defence is but a Faculty, and not properly termed a War; but we will not ſtick at the Name, but leave it as inſerted, and call the Faculty of Self-defence to be a waging War. And as Fencers, where the one attacks, and the other paryeth, yet both are ſtyled Fencers, and the Exerciſe is called Fencing. So thoſe that wage a War offenſive, and they that defend themſelves, are reciprocal Wagers of War.</p>
               <p>It is not to be queſtioned, but a Prince may take Arms to defend his own and Peoples Rights; for God, Man, and Reaſon, calls him to it, and are Incouragers of Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and to have recourſe to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152881:59"/>When nothing elſe will prevail, then the Offender muſt be Offended, and Force muſt repel Force. Yet though it be concluded reaſonable, and a Duty incumbent upon each to defend themſelves; nevertheleſs God hath indued Man with Wiſdom, by which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Things have been effected than by Force; for Prudence finds ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways to wind it ſelf out of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſuts Remedies to the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances then occurring. To give particular Obſervations for each caſe, is impoſſible ſince inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Affairs can only direct, for New Accidents require New Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. But there are Methods always of uſe, as Beacons to direct Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers. Amongſt the general Heads of Advices obſerve, That when you find you ſhall unavoidably be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked, and that all Means for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation avail not, then begin the Game yourſelf, and by way of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152881:59"/>prevention, if poſſible, aſſault your Enemy; for the ſureſt Defence, is Offence. Thus hurting, and being hurt, are near Neighbours. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what Meaſures Prudence may have directed, try alſo (even in the time of Action) what Money will do; part with it rather than with more Eſſentials. Let the Sheep be Shorn rather than part with their Skins; the Fruits of the Earth, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, are eaſilier retrieved, than Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Patrimonies. And though Ambition may not be charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down by Money, yet through the Means of Favourites, a Change hath many Times been compaſſed: Therefore Plough with the Aſpirers Heifers; for though the Ambitious one diſdain, Golden Showers, yet he may be overcome by a <hi>Dalila,</hi> or ſome Favourite.</p>
               <p>Uſe therefore Gold as being an Engine of great uſe; it is a moſt Soveraign Miſtreſs that makes the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152881:60"/>Blind See, and gives Strength to the Weak, and Feet and Wings to the Slow. By it Peace is ſometimes pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, and it is the cauſe of much Good, and much Evil; it is the Spring that ſets all Wheels on going, from the Prince to the meaneſt of his People.</p>
               <p>The Prince therefore ſhould not want this ſo admirable a Cordial ſutable to all the Grievances incident to a languiſhing and threatened State, and is the beſt Bullwark to fence off approaching Evils; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Famine, Fire, or Sword; it is ſo deſirable, that the Buſineſs of Mankind in all Ages hath been to acquire it. How hath it penetrated Rocks, Stony Hearts, melted Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals; and without other Key, hath cauſed to fly open the ſtrongeſt Gates to pay it homage, though tyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Aſs's Back?</p>
               <p>If the Tempeſt cannot be divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Gold, then ſee what Stores
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152881:60"/>and Proviſions have been laid up. Loſe no Time, it is an advantage to be ſooneſt in the Field; and if there be no want of Money, Counſel, nor other Requiſites, then he that gives the firſt Blow, being ſo provided, is liklier to renew his Stroak; than thoſe whom a Surpriſe hath brought into diſorder. Thus meet danger, elſe it will find you out, and give Reputation to your Courage and Strength; and may be of uſe to bring the Enemy to conſider, That a War built on Injuſtice may indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger his own Ruin. But let not him who values himſelf for Might, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, Numbers, Riches, and paſt Succeſſes, be too aſſured; for Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs doth not always ſerve the ſame Maſter, for ſometimes it hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that Victory hath waited on thoſe, whoſe Forces were Inferiour to the Aſſailant, whoſe numerous Multitudes threatened to Swallow all before them; yet as the ſmall
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152881:61"/>Sands ſtop the Career of the raging Seas, and ſet bounds to its proud and inſulting Waves, That <hi>ſo far they ſhall go and no farther,</hi> ſo ſhould all bordering concerned Ones, nay even all <hi>Europe,</hi> indeavour to chain up the never-ſatisfied Lion with prey, that thereby he may be confined to his due Bounds: But ſome preſume that Fortune will always favour their Purpoſes, ſo they continue Plagues in their Age.</p>
               <p>But when neither Money, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Meaſures, nor Force can reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue from Ruin, then the Giant muſt be let alone, and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites uſed to calm that Heat: For when Courage is not available, a prudent Shelter from approaching Danger may be commendable, and ought not to be ſtyled Cowardiſe; for though Vertue be moſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by wreſtling with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Difficulties, and that Courage is ready to frame Ideas, That all
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152881:61"/>Dangers are leſs, than what their Fears ſuggeſt them to be, whoſe falſe Images have often fetched Diſaſters from far, even to cauſe Armies to Fly when none Purſu'd; yet it is Fool-hardineſs to run precipitately into them, rather than ſeek a timely Remedy anſwerable to Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as by calling in Succours; which, if failing, then the Generous will chuſe rather to dye gloriouſly, than tamely lye down to be inſlaved; better it is to dye free by hazarding all in truſting Providence, than to be trodden under Foot. The All-powerfull is not tyed to Strength, or Numbers, but can place the Laurel on the Head of the weakeſt. And though Supplies be wanting, and that they exceed in number of Men, yet they may not in number of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: For a good Cauſe, and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, anſwers all Defects. As <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manzor,</hi> Son of an <hi>Arabian</hi> King, told his Father, That no Weapon
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152881:62"/>was too ſhort for a Man of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; ſince what it wanted in Length, it might be ſupplied by Valour, and ſtretching forth the Arm.</p>
               <p>And though Expectations may not immediately be anſwered, yet the Generous will perſevere in magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Reſolutions to the laſt, and not preſcribe a time for Deliverance; for he who is the Protector of the oppreſſed, uſually takes the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to deliver, when Extremity calls loudeſt. For there is no Fire, how great ſoever, but may be either quenched, or an entire Conflagrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on prevented: Few Wounds but find Plaiſters proper for their Sore. Beſides, Time wonderfully changes the Face of Things, and makes our very Paſſions alter, that that which once was the Object of our Hate may in time become that of Love, or at leaſt Indifferency; even the Perſons of the Aſſailants are not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152881:62"/>though their Paſſions may appear ſo.</p>
               <p>Thus Hopes ſhould bear up the Courage of the Generous, what ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is or may be in proſpect, any thing rather than deſpair; imagine that the Aſſailant, or his Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity may dye, or his Paſſion for Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire ceaſe, or that ſome unforeſeen Accident may turn the Scales; for though Towns, Cities, and Countreys may ſuffer, be Stormed, and Taken, yet they can not carry them away; and Time may either ſee them ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, or retaken.</p>
               <p>Neither is it morally impoſſible, but that even the Conquerours may be Conquered by thoſe they oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for the greateſt Things are many times brought about by ſmall Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents: There needs but the want of Water, or a too great Inundation of the ſame, to change the face of things; for when God will deliver a People, his Methods are uſually attended
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152881:63"/>with ſurpriſing Circumſtances, the better to ſhew that his Finger opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therein. Yet let not the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome ſurpriſing Deliverance, render ſecure, but be armed for Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, and uſe all probable means. However averſe Fortune may appear to be, yet keep Courage awake, and perſevere patiently: For there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more inconſtant than the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents of War; the knowlegde of which, may be improved ſo, as in Proſperity never to be ſecure, nor in Adverſity to ſink. But hope ſtill, and be diligent, and active as fire, and with the Eagle quick-ſighted, <hi>Argus</hi> like, looking every way; and, as if poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of <hi>Briareus</hi>'s many Arms, beſtir your ſelf to fruſtrate all Enterpriſes.</p>
               <p>The Fore-ſight of events is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and prevents many Evils, for by ſeaſonable notices, Places are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed, and Peoples Effects ſecured. This may detect the Imprudence of thoſe, who through a parſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152881:63"/>Principle of ſparing lye ſtill, as the unconcerned Object of Prey to thoſe, who are upon no other ſcore an Enemy, than that their Ambition and Power makes them ſuch. It concerns all who are Neighbours to ſuch a Danger, to ſtand on their Guard, and to ſtrengthen themſelves by joint Confederacy, againſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Oppreſſour, who hath given the World occaſion to know, he will never want Pretences to offend, if thereby he may cloth himſelf with the Spoil of others; who is never in the wrong, nor yet true to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; and will never want inſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ways to involve the Unwary; who like the Fox, or Wolf are for making all a Prey they can Surpriſe. Therefore by Union, and Counſel ſtrengthen each other; for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Counſel anſwers the want of Force. Being thus armed by Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, go on and Proſper; for that is the beſt Armour of Proof.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:152881:64"/>
               <p>Upon all occaſions where Hoſtile Actions are neceſſary, as many uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Hands are to be ſecured as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; but let few Heads be privy to what ſhall be the Enterpriſe. Affairs of War ought to be deliberated by many, but the Reſults known to few. When all lies at Stake, as Life, Liberty and Safety, then it is high time to ſtand up for them; eſpecially having to do with One, who regards not ſuch trifles as Honour, and Conſcience; and looks upon Juſtice, and the keeping Promiſes, to be plebeian Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, offenſive to a ſqueemiſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and a ſtop to the Career of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cummulating Provinces, as ſo many Annexes to his Territories; but how far it conſiſts with Juſtice, that is never made the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Thus it appears reaſonable, that in time of Peace, Forces ſhould be maintained, and Diſciplined; who ought not to be conſidered by the Inhabitants, as their Diſeaſe; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152881:64"/>as thoſe in whom conſiſts their Safety and Happineſs: For a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent number of ſtanding Forces, kept in due order; inſtead of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jealouſies, and being a Terrour, ought to be conſidered as the Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks of the Country; and as the great Incouragement to Induſtry. For what Courage can the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man have to Plough and Sow, or the Merchant to venture his Stock, to Traffick, when they know not who ſhall reap the Fruit of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry? Thus under God the Souldier is the Subjects ſhelter, from Fears at home, and from Enemies abroad; by whoſe means Trade Floriſhes, and the Age is Crowned with Plenty. By what hath been ſaid, it appears, That a ſtanding Army kept in good Order and Diſcipline, may be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of Juſtice, and the Protector of the Soveraign's Authority; by which he bears the Character of God's Vicegerent on Earth.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:152881:65"/>
               <p>My ſpare Hours, have given me occaſion to ſpeak of Peace and War, which I intended for the private uſe of my Succeſſors, who are not in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection tomeet with a favorabler Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception from the World, than my Predeceſſors, and ſelf have had. I hope my Neighbouring Princes, from the ſame Inducement, may find Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to join in Confederacy, againſt formidable Incroachers; in after Ages, as well as in theſe our times, which will ſtrengthen this received rule, That from others Harms, and paſt Dangers; it is wiſdom to take Warning: And moſt certain it is, That in the Union of leſſer Powers conſiſts their Strength. For though War, like ſome Phyſick is never to be Adminiſtered, but upon unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Occaſions; yet it is neceſſary to Bridle the exorbitant Deſires of the Ambitious, and to preſerve Peace. Thus War though a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Evil, yet hath this Good in it;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152881:65"/>in that it protects the Weak from threatened Violence, ſecures Juſtice to each Proprietor. Thus taking up Arms, may be ſometimes a moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Refuge; when by Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Inundations the Prince is Inſulted.</p>
               <p>I might here have concluded, but having obſerved the frailty of Peace when Unarmed; and that ſecurity is a temptation for Inſulters to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by their lying ſo expoſed: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the uſe of Arms, is of abſolute Neceſſity, even in time of Peace, and that the Military Art be incouraged. For which Reaſon, I ſhall further add ſome thing with reference to Military Profeſſors, and will deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher the Qualifications requiſite in each of its Members; for as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Imployment exceeds all others, ſo its Profeſſors deſerve the greateſt Honours and Incouragements. There is no Virtue in Civil Society that heaps ſo much Glory on the Heads of thoſe it adorns, as that of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152881:66"/>the Military, and Experience hath taught Men to know, That it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to have an eſtabliſhed Policy, with ſutable Incouragements anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the great Undertakings of military Men; that according to the different Spheres they move in, they may have ſutable Returns, without which few would be found to court ſo dangerous a Miſtreſs, that cannot be obtained but by wading through Bloud, Sweat, and Labour, whoſe Rivals for Honour never floriſh ſo gloriouſly, nor ride in Triumph ſo pompouſly, as in the midſt of Fire and Smoke. To proced, let ſome thing be firſt ſaid of the Infantry in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and after, of each of their Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the uſe of Infantry.</head>
               <p>THe Foot is uſeful in all Places, though rough, narrow, or ſtraight Paſſages, whether Hilly,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152881:66"/>Rocky, or Boggy Grounds, and is of leſs charge in raiſing and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and its Stores lye in leſs room, and require fewer Carriages, and are eaſilier diſpoſed of, and ſecured, than Forage. When the Foot is well Diſciplined, and in good Heart, they will maintain their Ground a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Horſe, and are beſt in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, Sieges, and Ambuſhes, and will bear the brunt of the Day, with more Obſtinacy; and though they are not ſo expeditious in gaining Victory, nor ſo uſeful in purſuing; yet they are not ſo ſoon vanquiſhed, but will ſtand the hotteſt Brunts longer, and indure Fatigues, with Reſolution and Patience; when the Horſe-man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Maſter of his own Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if hurryed away by theſe ſtrong-headed Animals, to the diſhonour of their Riders, and many times loſs of Victory. In the Infantry are more Preferments, and is the readieſt way to the higheſt Military Honours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:152881:67"/>
               <head>Of the Common Souldier.</head>
               <p>HE is the Stock upon which all Cions are ingrafted, where the Product ſometimes exceeds its Parent, who from thence have riſen to the higheſt Degrees of Honour; even Princes have honoured that Station, either by ſhouldering the Muſquet, or trailing the Pike.</p>
               <p>The Common Souldier ought to be young and vigourous, of a heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Conſtitution able to indure Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues; ſuch who have been inured to Labour and Hardſhips are moſt deſirable; the Climates that they are born under, may contribute much to indure Hardſhips; for more are killed for not being able to ſuffer Fatigues, than have loſt their Lives by the Sword. His Stature ſhould be rather tall than little; his Limbs clean and ſtrong; his Feet good, and of a nimble and active Body; cleanly in his Perſon Cloths and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152881:67"/>Arms; well Shod, and careful of his Neceſſaries, That he may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter Want, with the longeſt. He muſt not hazard at Play, what he hath, leſt it becomes another's Propriety, and ſo be tempted to ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular Ways, to ſupply his Wants; which may expoſe him to ſuffer mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Diſcipline. Thus the braveſt in a Heard have been untimely cut off, as Examples to others, which but for evil Preſidents, hath been deſired, that they might have been ſpared.</p>
               <p>Alſo Wine and Women, are the bane of an Army, and unfit the Souldier for Duty; the firſt bereaves him of Senſes, and the ſecond of Strength, and both are Triflers away of time, and Obſtructions to Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement.</p>
               <p>The Character of a Souldier is, That he have Courage as to dare Look Death and Danger, in the Face. One who is armed with Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, either to vanquiſh, or Dye.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152881:68"/>It hath been obſerved, That ſome Men, who have Courage in the Field, will fight like Heroes in a Crowd, when animated by numbers; yet will want that mettle in private Quarrels. It were to be deſired, our Souldier were of that rugged Mould, not to ſuffer Affront, nor give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for Quarrels; but when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted over, then let him only right himſelf by generous Repulſes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he gains eſteem, and ſhuts the Door againſt after Broils and, Quarrels.</p>
               <p>His Character is accompliſhed if he Knowes to carry himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonairly to his Equals, obediently and humbly to his Superiours, and can give Inſtances of his Humanity to all.</p>
               <p>He is haughty to the Proud and Inſolent: With his Enemies ſtout and valiant; but is meek and gentle, and affable, when Time, Perſons, and Place call for it.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:152881:68"/>
               <p>He is alſo vigilant, and a ſtrict Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of his Duty, fearing to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, either by his Superiours or Enemies, and never queſtions why, or what are the Reaſons; but with an implicit Obedience, without murmuring, diſcharges thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands injoined him.</p>
               <p>He will keep his Arms in good order, and readineſs; and, with the many good Qualities requiſite, he is indued with Patience, a moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Ingredient in a Souldier; ſo that Money is not more uſeful, to ſupply the Neceſſities of the Poor, nor Wiſdom to anſwer the Defects of Folly, than Patience and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence is, in the courſe of a Military Life; for by this Vertue the greateſt Difficulties are overcome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:152881:69"/>
               <head>Of the Corporal.</head>
               <p>HE is promoted to that Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from that of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldier; ſo ought to have his Qualifications, with improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; as he exceeds him in Ttruſt repoſed; ſo he ought to go beyond him, in Diligence and Capacity. That he may the better diſcipline the private Centinels, and keep, Peace he is to give information of Things to his Superiours, and carry the Liſt of ſuch as are to mount the Guard. It is he that diſtributes Ammunition, and Proviſion, and provides neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Fire and Candle, and gives the Word handed to him; and in a particular manner his Duty is, to be acquainted with the Perſons, and merit of each Particular, that he may place them accordingly.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:152881:69"/>
               <p>The Truſt repoſed in a Corporal, is of that conſequence, That on his Fidelity, depends the Security of thoſe Avenues where he is placed; for to have <hi>corps de gardes</hi> ſurpriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is of that importance, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it hath occaſioned the Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction of an Army.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Sergeant.</head>
               <p>HE is one choſen by the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, from amongſt the beſt of his Men, for known Fidelity, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, Courage, and Diligence; he is the Corporal's Elder Brother, whoſe Place differs in this, That he Hands to him his Inſtructions, and gives out thoſe Ammunitions and Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons deſigned, and with the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, takes cogniſance of the merit of each particular Perſon; and their Lodging, and Neceſſities, of which
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152881:70"/>an Inſpection ought to be taken, as alſo into their Behaviour; to aſſign Quarters, which he is to viſit from time to time. The Care of the Company lies on him; he is the Captain's Eyes and Ears, by whom he receives Information of both Sick and Well, and other neceſſary Circumſtances. In ſhort, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant ought to be brave and ſtout every where, Night and Day, mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, walking the Rounds, viſiting Centinels; and, when upon Duty, he is to be perſonally preſent with the Superiour Officers, at the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſhutting of the Gates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Enſign.</head>
               <p>IT is a Poſt for a Gentleman; he ought to be endued with Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of Honour for his Country, and Perſon. He ſhould be Young,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152881:70"/>a Man of Courage, well made, with a good Preſence. His Duty is, to carry the Colours where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and chuſe rather to part with his Life, than with them. In the abſence of his Captain, and Lieutenant, his Duty is the ſame with theirs, whoſe Inſtructions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in common theſe do refer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Lieutenant.</head>
               <p>IN the Captain's Abſence, he is his Repreſentative; ſo requires all his Qualifications, their Duties being the ſame. He diſciplineth the Men, hath regard that the Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants diſcharge their Duty. The Care of the Company lieth in a great meaſure on him; therefore he ſhould be Prudent, and a Man of Courage, as well as of Experience: For if the Captain falls in Combat,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152881:71"/>he leaves the rear to the next Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant, to take his Sword and Poſt, at the Head of the Company. It is his great Intereſt to keep a good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with his Captain; being the way to Prefrement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Captain.</head>
               <p>HE ſhould be a Perſon of Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Courage, and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; prudent in Matters, neither too rough, nor too indulgent, that he incur neither Hatred, nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. He ought to be informed of his Men's Names, and of their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſhould know their Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. He marches at the Head of his Company, and leads them on and off in Action, and he is to know the Quantity of Arms, Time when, and Place where, and all other Circumſtances, according to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152881:71"/>the Nature of the Occaſion Alſo he ſhould be skilled in Fortifications.</p>
               <p>This Poſt is the uſual Step, by which the greateſt military Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours are aſcended; therefore he ought to be a Man of worth, ſuch as ſhall diſdain the conſulting his own Eaſe at a time when his Men are incommoded; he ſhould be qualifyed with Wiſdom, carrying always a Face of Proſperity, even in the midſt of Diſcouragements, that none be diſheartened. He ſhould have a Spirit above mean Things, as that of making advantage of his Men by falſe Muſters; but with the <hi>Centurion</hi> in the Goſpel, keep his Company compleat; it being upon Record to his Honour, that he had a Hundred Men. By which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, as if there had been no Falſe Muſters in thoſe Days. Alſo to aſſiſt his Men by little Advances, may keep them from Irregularities, and gain their Love. He ſhould
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152881:72"/>be ambitious of honourable Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, and not incourage by his Example any exceſs, but puniſh Drinking, and the Quarrelſome, with all Makers of Parties; Theft and the Seditious, are to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, or cut off for Example, by a ſolemn and publick Execution. Small Faults need not be obſerved, and when ſuch as you would ſpare are guilty, ſo that the Eye cannot be ſhut, without incurring the Cenſure of being partial, then Severity is to be uſed, anſwerable to the Nature of the Crime without reſpect of Perſons; and as a Parent, who, though he may have a ſecret ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to ſome of his Children, above the reſt; yet he wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceals it, and with Caution incour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages all, and diſobliges none.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:152881:72"/>
               <head>Of the Major.</head>
               <p>HIs Character is in common with other Commiſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Officers, <hi>viz.</hi> That he have Courage, and be qualifyed with Knowledge; and that he be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and active; for in the Major's Power is included that of all the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in the Regiment, which gives him authority over the Captains, and other inferiour Officers, as well as Souldiers, in Garriſons, Villages, and in the Field. If there be not a Major in the Garriſon; then he receives the Word, and directions from the Governour, as to Hours, Place and Quarters, which he communicates to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants, the ſame as if in Villages, or in the Field, whoſe Duty, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions vary, according to the diſpoſedneſs of Places, and the time when, whether of Danger, or
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152881:73"/>otherwiſe. He appoints detatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Places for Rendezvous, and marks out their Incampments, and hands to the Officers their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, before whom he is to be at their aſſigned Quarters, where he detatches <hi>corps de Gardes,</hi> and appoints Places for Centinels. His Orders are not to be altered but by himſelf as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ordinary Conduit for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing them, either from the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, or his Colonel. He ſhould diſcourage uſeleſs Perſons, and ſee the Regiment march in due order, and that thy keep their Ranks, and carry their Arms, except weary, or ſick; for whoſe relief, his care is, That carriages be provided to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that ſuch as lag behind may be received. It is alſo his place to give out Proviſions to each Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany their Dividend, and to anſwer the neceſſity of the Sick, by ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupplies of Food, Phyſick, and Shelter.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:152881:73"/>
               <p>In Sieges he advertiſes the Officers of his Regiment when to mount the Guard, and Trenches, and commands the bringing off and on La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers; he keeps a Liſt of the Men, and takes Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the Officer's Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage. He is obliged to be every where, and ſo for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition's-ſake rides; he ſhould be often with his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Officers to receive Inſtructions. He ſets Prizes on what Sutlers bring in the Camp, and provides for their ſafe Conduct, and that they may not want he doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage their being paid.</p>
               <p>His Buſineſs conſiſts more in giving Orders, than in executing Exploits; and though the practical part be requiſit, yet a thorow Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152881:74"/>of the Theory is of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Neceſſity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Colonel.</head>
               <p>HE is ſuppoſed to have eminently all the Qualifications of a brave Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, who hath gone through thoſe Degrees of Command, which have capacitated him for that Poſt, leſt a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enciouſneſs of Demerit occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion his envying of more experienc'd Commanders that act under him. He is to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack, and defend, and lead his Regiment to ingage, to make Retreats and Intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; he relieves Poſts, viſits Works, cauſes Orders to be obſerved, and hath the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152881:74"/>Care of the wounded Officers. He hath Power to arreſt, and ſuſpend thoſe in Commiſſion under him. He ſhould be of an attractive and obliging Comportment to gain Love, and to preſerve his Eſteem he muſt act with Bravery, Courage, and Prudence, and be ever armed with Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Major-General.</head>
               <p>HE is to the Army in a great Character that which a private <hi>Major</hi> is in a Regiment; he ought to have the General's Ear, and to be ready to receive, and with Expedition to convey Orders received.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:152881:75"/>
               <head>Of the Field-Marſhal.</head>
               <p>IT is of abſolute Neceſſity that he that moves in this Poſt ſhould be a Perſon of Worth, Honour, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, ſince good or evil Accidents may happen, or be prevented, according to his managing his Orders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the General: He appoints Guards, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys, Parties and Marches, and diſtributes his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions amongſt the Majors. He ſhould be informed of the Country through which the March is intended; the Care of lodging the Army lies on him, where he is to be the firſt and laſt mounted: This
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152881:75"/>is ſo neceſſary and painful a Poſt, that in all Armies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly as they are nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous an Augmentation of them is required, they being an Eaſe to the General, who are to ſee Orders kept, and Juſtice adminiſtered. As the Majors and other Officers Care are of thoſe leſſer Bodies under their Command, ſo the Field-Marſhal's Care is required of the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; ſo that Experience and Conduct ſeems as neceſſary to one in this Poſt, as to that of the Lieutenant-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals.</p>
               <p>He is alſo the Protector of Sutlers, the Moderator of Rates, that the one may be incouraged to bring Supplies, and yet the Soldier not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. He orders the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152881:76"/>Marches of Foot and Horſe, their Quarters, and their Form of Battel, according to the then diſpoſal of Things in reference to Place, Time, and numbers of Horſe and Foot, the better to prevent what Evil may happen, or to make the beſt of the worſt of Accidents. This Place of Field-Marſhal is expoſed to Envy, and Cenſure, ſo is a Station of more Honour and Care, than Satisfaction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:152881:76"/>
               <head>Of the Lieutenant-General.</head>
               <p>THis Poſt, and the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, and Field-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals, have ſo great an Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that there is requiſite the ſame Capacity, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Qualifications; for what the General commands, the other executes, and that ſometimes in ſeparate Bodies, and on ſeveral Occaſions, as with Flying Camps, at Sieges, Attacks, and with Detachments and Convoys. The General as the Spring doth cauſe the Motion of all the Wheels, the principal of which are the Lieutenant-Generals, ſo ſhould be Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of tried Fidelity, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152881:77"/>and Ability. Their Numbers are incertain, they act according to the General's Orders, which they hand to others, as in relation to Marches, aſſigning Incamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Decampments, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Ingagements, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Retreats and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits; therefore Foreſight, Prudence, Courage, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and a preſence of Mind in the greateſt Hurry, are their requiſite Qualifications.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:152881:77"/>
               <head>OF THE CAVALRY.</head>
               <p>HORSE is ſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in an Army, that good Succeſs in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure depends thereon, for all Places are firſt poſſeſſed by them, and thoſe that exceed in their Numbers are likelieſt to become Maſters of the Field; for by them Gariſons are victualled, the Army provided with Forrage, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys, Parties, and Quarters beaten up, ſurpriſed, and ſometimes carried away: By the Horſe it is that the Enemy is ſtreightened, the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152881:78"/>Country ravaged, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſed by Incurſions. There is not an Enterprize of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and Difficulty where the Horſe is not concerned; by their means Deſigns are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed, facilitated, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited.</p>
               <p>The Horſe being ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, ſo many of them are to be had as may anſwer the proportion of your Foot, as well as that of the Enemies. According to whoſe different Characters and Uſefulneſſes they are ordered, whether as <hi>Cuiraſſiers, Light-horſe, Dragoons, Croates,</hi> or <hi>Heydukes.</hi> By theſe Paſſes are ſeized, Blocades made, and Contributions raiſed, Marches expedited, Purſuits and Surpriſes given; in the expeditious executing of which they are more
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152881:78"/>neceſſary, and exceed the Foot, whoſe ſlow Motions are often Impediments, and cauſe Diſappointments, while the Horſe by their quick and long Marches are the great Advantage, though attended with Inconveniencies, as being a greater Care and Charge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Trooper.</head>
               <p>THis Poſt, though the loweſt, yet from thence ſome have aſcended to the higheſt Degree of Honour in Military Imploys; and as the ſame Soil produces Grain of ſeveral ſorts, ſo the Buſh and the Palm hath the ſame Origine, for Virtue is not
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152881:79"/>always found in elevated Fortunes, nor will that Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious DAME be confined to Pallaces, but the Country Cottage doth ſometimes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the World Heroes, who from their Clods of Earth, their Ploughs and Spades, have aſcended to the height of Honour.</p>
               <p>Theſe Conſiderations ought to quicken thoſe in the moſt inferiour Station to be Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators of thoſe Enſamples of Virtue gone before them, and incourage themſelves with Hopes, that by a patient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering in Well-doing, tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Steps, having Incouragements with Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, they may juſtly aſpire at that Honour and Glory, that others before them have compaſſed.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:152881:79"/>
               <p>But as his Mind ſhould be aſpiring, and qualified with Courage and Bravery, being undaunted, fearing nothing but Shame; and as his Inſide is adorned with generous Virtues, ſo his Outſide ſhould alſo have that of a comely Preſence, ſtrong and manly, rather tall than little, and uſed to the Fatigues of riding; not ſuch as are taken from Towns or Cities, where, by an effeminate Life, they are made tender, and unfit for the Hardſhips of a Camp. He ſhould be young in Years, from Twenty to Forty; for Nature gives ſuch Impreſſions to Age, that ill Habits are not eaſily rectified; but an old Trooper is a uſeful Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber if grown ſo under Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, whoſe Skill in Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152881:80"/>need not be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, which Knowledge all ſhould at firſt bring with them. As the choice of the Man is made, ſo ſhould alſo the Horſe in ſome meaſure correſpond; who ſhould nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be young nor old, but ſtrong-ſet, well-limbed, and not of a great heavy make, yet large, and full cheſted, ſhort, and ſtrongly coupled and jointed, of clean Limbs, and good Feet, ſuch as will ſtand Fire: It is in <hi>Germany</hi> where Horſes fit for Military Service moſt abound nor will any ſtand Fire like them.</p>
               <p>As the Horſeman is to be under the Command of his Superiour, ſo he ought to have the Command of his Horſe, that neither Gun nor
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152881:80"/>Drum ſhall diſorder nor make him break his Rank. Our Trooper ſhould be as careful of his Horſe, as of himſelf, and by being diligent, careful and obedient to Order, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Captain more than his Enemy, he may come to attain to that Preferment that his Merit calls for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Brigadier, or Corporal.</head>
               <p>THE Captain ſingles him out from among the eldeſt of the Troopers, as judging him beſt qualified and experienced; he is to the Horſe, what a Corporal or Serjeant is to the Foot; in the Quartermaſter's Abſence he ſupplieth his Place. To
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152881:81"/>diſcharge his Duty well he muſt be no Stranger to Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: It is from him that the Captain expects an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all Omiſſions and Diſorders, with a Liſt of the Horſe and Men, and of the Condition they are in. When upon Duty, by the Major's Order, he ſets the Vedetes, whom he directs; to prevent Remiſneſs he often viſits, and in due time relieves them. It is his Province to inſtruct the Troopers, alſo what For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Proviſions are hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him from the Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, he diſtributes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:152881:81"/>
               <head>Of the Quarter-maſter.</head>
               <p>HE is as a Steward to the Troop, ſo ſhould be prudent, intelligent and faithful, being intruſted with their Subſiſtence. Courage, Reſolution and Diligence, ought to be his Qualifications; from him is expected a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Liſt of the Mens Names, and Places from whence they are, with whom he is to reckon, pay, and diſcount. He ſets down the Orders given him by his Officers, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits the Mens Quarters and Stables, and doth ſee that all be in Order from the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the leaſt of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couterments, that from the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152881:82"/>Bridle to a Girth there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting. The Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition alſo is his Care, which he diſtributes, whether in the Field or Garriſons, and takes Care that their Quarters be ready before their arrival. He is to be at the Captains Quarters Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to carry the Orders he hath received from his Major. He commands Detachments, and conducts them to their Place of Rendezvous.</p>
               <p>His great Buſineſs is to ſee that the Troopers live in their Quarters in good order, and that Complaints be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced, and Grievances re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed.</p>
               <p>Thus by keeping good Quarter, and aſſigning Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he hath given him the Name of <hi>Quarter-maſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:152881:82"/>
               <head>Of the Cornet.</head>
               <p>THis Poſt is the firſt Step to Honour, being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſive is fit only for ſuch as have Eſtates, or are Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. This Station is not ſo troubleſome as honourable, and ſhould be filled up by a Man of Quality, as his firſt Eſſay; and if he hath before made a Campaign as a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunteer, he is the fitter for this Poſt: But tho' Favour ſhould have introduced him, yet if his Inclination were the moving Cauſe, Succeſs may be expected; for where generous Sentiments do put upon queſt for Glory, there Obedience will become eaſy,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152881:83"/>and he will readily execute his Superiour's Orders, and will ſet all his good Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations on work to compaſs his deſired end.</p>
               <p>There is in a natural Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity to a deſired Object an occult quality that leads Soul, Body, and all its Faculties, like a Torrent with Impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity to it, ſo that when Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Honour is the Thing aimed at, from thence may reaſonably be expected great Things.</p>
               <p>It is the Cornet's Duty to carry the Standard when the Troop marches, as at Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, at the Guards, and in Battel he is to bear it himſelf, and Death ſhould rather be his Choice, than part with that Badge of Honour, ſince his Perſonal Reputation, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152881:83"/>that of his Troop, depends thereon. If at any time he ſuffers it to be carried, it ought to be by one of the ſtouteſt, and comelieſt in the Troop. In the Lieutenans's Abſence he commands. He is to ſhew ſubmiſſive Reſpects to his Superiors, and to carry himſelf obligingly to all; for to make Friends, and to have no Enemies, is the way to Preferment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Lieutenant.</head>
               <p>HE is the Captain's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, in whoſe Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence he hath the Care of the Troop, ſo ſhould have Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, Experience and Prudence to know how to act in his
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:152881:84"/>place. He gives Information of Omiſſions or Commiſſions, and of all that relates to the Troop. To make the better Inſpection he viſits the Men, and views their Horſes, and recommends to them the care of their Arms as well as Horſes, and ſhould carry himſelf ſo as to be loved and feared. The <hi>Brigadier</hi> and <hi>Quarter-maſter</hi> are to be incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and countenanced by him in performing their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that nothing be ſuffered to be amiſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:152881:84"/>
               <head>Of the Captain of Horſe.</head>
               <p>VVIth the Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Courage and Conduct, he is to have Experience in his own, and others Buſineſs; he leads his Troop where commanded, and accordingly gives Orders to thoſe under him; he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs, and leads his Men on, and off, and takes Care they be well mounted, and armed, that all be in good order. He diſcourages Debauchery as the Weakener of Purſe and Body, and the inlet to Pilfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Effeminacy; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent which, hard Duty and frequent Exerciſes may be conducing. The good Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152881:85"/>will therefore himſelf ſee that his Men be duly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, that upon any ſudden occaſion they may be fit to be drawn out for Service<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He will incourage Well doers, and give publick Marks of Favour to provoke Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to make themſelves wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the like, by which means he will gain Love, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when his Men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that they are perſonally by Name taken notice of. Our Captain, if indued with a generous Soul, doth influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thoſe about him to give him Reſpect and Eſteem; for whoſe Heart would not run after him that values Virtue and Honour more, than all the World beſides, even than Life it ſelf, which he regards not when the Publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152881:85"/>and his Reputation is the Queſtion?</p>
               <p>It is not to be doubted but he that moves in this Station, hath by long Service and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Merit attained this Poſt, where before having learned to obey, he knows the better to command, and upon all Occaſions how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf whether under good or bad Events, ſo as that he will not give oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, nor ſuffer any to be let ſlip, but will take hold of all Occaſions, and give the Enemies none.</p>
               <p>Being thus qualified he will be feared, and obeyed, which in Military Affairs is of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity; for though ſome Injunctions may ſeem to be but of ſmall moment, and that their Non-obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152881:86"/>may appear to be a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of no Conſequence, yet little Omiſſions often prove fatal; therefore all Orders ſhould be punctually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Colonel of Horſe.</head>
               <p>IT is expected he be a Man of Honour, Merit and Experience; if he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly commanded in the Foot Service, he is the fitter for this Station. He leads the Regiment to Action whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Van, Rear-guard, or main Body; and if Merit hath introduced him, then he marches with the more aſſurance. His great Care ſhould be, that all under his
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152881:86"/>Command diſcharge their Duty, that nothing be wrongs, but that his Prince be well ſerved, and that Things be ſo carried, that his Honour may not ſuffer any Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, therefore he will have the Men often drawn up, exerciſed, and muſtered, and will rather have Supernume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raries, than that his Numbers ſhould not be compleat.</p>
               <p>It is the Honour of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel that it ſhould be ſo; it is his Credit to have his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment well Manned, mounted and armed; ſome would chuſe rather to retrench from their own Property, than ſuffer any defect in their Power to redreſs: Which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Pride is not preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to their particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; for when the time of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152881:87"/>disbanding comes, thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments are likelieſt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, where each Man looks like an Officer, and each Officer like a General Commander; and upon a View they will have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honourable Encomiums from their Prince, but in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood will be of thoſe that ſhall be retained when other Regiments ſhall be broken. Thus by making others do their Duty, he diſcharges his own, and thereby deſerves the Name of Colonel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:152881:87"/>
               <head>Of the Major-General of Horſe.</head>
               <p>IT is highly conducible for the good of the Army, that thoſe in this Poſt be qualified, for the executive part depends on him, which is the more difficult from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening Accidents, change of Place, and from Reports; therefore good Senſe, Courage and Conduct, ſhould not be wanting, for the receiving and giving Orders is his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and upon good Grounds he gives Information of all Proceedings even to ſmall Accidents; all which, to prevent Miſtakes, ſhould be ſet down in writing.</p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:152881:88"/>
               <p>Thus the Major-General muſt join with Force Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and with his Courage Skill, and couple the Foxes Tail and Lyon's Skin toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Lieutenant-General of Horſe.</head>
               <p>HE ſhould be a Perſon cut out by Nature for great Things, one whoſe Experience and Judgment ſhould be ſuch, that all Things may be eaſy to him, who being verſed in every Man's Duty, and having Courage, is placed thereby above being in a Hurry tho' in the midſt of Confuſion; then it is that Judgment
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:152881:88"/>may be of greater uſe than the Sword.</p>
               <p>When Perſons are elevated to this Station, if they have Perſonal Merit their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will be much more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, than if Birth, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or Elderſhip had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred them. Perſons thus qualified are deſervedly ſtiled the Generals Eyes and Hands, for they do act as Occaſion and Prudence requires, as well in reference to offend, as defend, or to ſecure the Camp, and anſwer Supplies. His Care is awake Night and Day for Camp and Quarters, to ſurprize or prevent Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes, which being regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed whatever the Succeſs may be, yet he loſes no Honour; and though En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy ſpeaks well of none, yet
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:152881:89"/>his Courteſie, Affability and Humanity to all, with Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity and ſeaſonable Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, accompanied with a free and an open Table, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer even Malice it ſelf, and make the moſt malevolent join in Ecchoing forth the Commendations of this our Captain, who in this ſhews himſelf great, in that he acts and lives like himſelf, as well in Quality as Merit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:152881:89"/>
               <head>Of the General.</head>
               <p>IT may be ſaid, That he is not only one of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, but even ſometimes the one of more than a hundred thouſand; and ſo deſerving he may be, as to be more worth than many thouſands of the reſt. Such was the Voice of the People in <hi>David</hi>'s time, they very well knew that the Body muſt ſuffer in common with their Head, therefore their Care was in a particular manner to preſerve that, as the Means on which their Preſervation depended. As he is the greateſt ſo he ought to be the moſt excellent in all Heroick Qualifications,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:152881:90"/>and Noble by Birth. Tho' this Poſt may be conferred as a Recompence to Virtue and Merit, where noble Birth is not, yet this Place is beſt adorned when filled by a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Honour, and one that is born great, whoſe Quality ſhall give him a Reputation, which when therewith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with Virtue, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Conduct, Liberality, and Affability, and theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with an awful Majeſtick Mean, he ſhall thereby influence Love and Fear in all concerned with him. As he is the greateſt ſo he ought to be the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, which Deſert will ſet a Luſtre on all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and Actions. This eminent Poſt in which he moves, makes all good and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:152881:90"/>evil Succeſſes to be moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably his, and as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſo the Faults lie at his door. There are few Faults, but the Conſequences of them are ſmall in compariſon of thoſe committed in Military Affairs; for where an Army is routed, and thouſands cut down, Countries and Towns pillaged, deſtroyed and burnt, beſides the diſhonour of a ſhameful Flight, and ſneak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Holes and Corners, whilſt the Enemy rides in Triumph over Bag and Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and the Honour and Reputation of the Conquered, which ſiniſter Accident is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſo many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, that the Loſt and Diſhonour is ſeldom or never retrieved, except Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair gives new wings to <hi>Action.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:152881:91"/>
               <p>But when Succeſs follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our Hero at the Heels how honourable is it in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to himſelf, and how uſeful to his Prince, and Country, which gives occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for his being regiſtered in Hiſtory, where Poſterity finds him a Monument of Fame left on Record for future Ages to imitate. In ſhort, as his Faults are irreparable, and cauſe Sadneſſes, Sorrows, Tears and Lamentations, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and Slaveries; ſo the contrary gives Joy even to Tranſports, and fills the Mouths of each with Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and Expreſſions of Praiſe; and whereas the one hath Death and Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions writ in the Countenance, ſo the other hath painted Joy and Gladneſs, to which every
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:152881:91"/>Motion of their Bodies are ſo many Contributes to expreſs it.</p>
               <p>Thus it appears requiſite, That the General be not only great as to his Birth, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as to his Perſonal Merit; and to ſay all, a Soldier, who with theſe Qualifications if attended with Succeſs, will have his Head crowned with Honour. But if Fortune prove unconſtant, then the moſt reaſonable Attempts will be condemned, though he may deſerve by his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct more Honour than the Conqueror. But why ſpeak I of Fortune, as if Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence did not predominate over Human Affairs? This Fortune is no more than a Chimera, the Idol of Fools, for though Succeſs be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:152881:92"/>to her, yet it is God that gives the Victory; it is not always, to the Wiſe, nor the Strong, nor yet to Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to whom Succeſs is given, God reſerves to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the diſpoſal of Victory that none might boaſt. But ſingle Inſtances of God's Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er are not to be relied on; for tho' he hath been pleaſed to give Victory by diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Means, as that one ſhould kill a thouſand, and a few put ten thouſand to Flight, yet in our Days we have no Reaſon to expect ſuch Miracles, but rather Deliverances, by a courſe of means which God himſelf hath appointed, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by his Examples to Mankind, not ſuffering his own Armies (among whom
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:152881:92"/>he had ſet up his Standard) to enter upon Action in their promiſed Land, till they were become a Multitude; and we may as well expect Health and length of Days, without Food and Phiſick, as Preſervation in War with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out neceſſary Preſervatives; among which Preſervatives, the wiſe General deſerves the firſt Place, as being the chief Means, if qualified, and for thoſe other Neceſſaries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired they muſt be had in readineſs in time; thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well ſupplied, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and the Duty wiſely and faithfully diſcharged, the Succeſs muſt be left to God.</p>
               <p>Since Military Means are ſo neceſſary, and that the General is the Head, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:152881:93"/>he is ſuppoſed to have Qualifications to fit him for Action, and to command People, and Countries at home and abroad, and that he have a Tincture of Literature and Arts, that he be not impoſed on by bold Recommenders of Trifles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Alſo to be provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and liberal, are requiſite Qualifications. He ſhould be a Prince in his Temper, yet ſparing where Reaſon calls for it, not believing himſelf leſſened by taking Cognizance of the minuteſt Things relating to good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, that Stores be not waſted: The preventing Spoil and Havock is as much the Province of a General, as thoſe more ſublime Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Battels, Sieges and Surpriſes; by good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:152881:93"/>and a provident Care, Multitudes may be preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Want and ſiniſter Accidents. Alſo the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, with his other Acquire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhould know the Country where the Seat of War may be carried on, therefore in time of Peace Rural Recreations, as Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Hawking, may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Knowledge; by which means he may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Incloſures, Uneavenneſs of Ground, the Champion Country, Marches, Roads, narrow Paſſages, the Knowledge of which is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to all Military Men. To be an accompliſhed Captain is obtained by great Labour and Induſtry; and though they may be born Soldiers, yet Experience is not attained
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:152881:94"/>but by Care and Application, as appears by the great Work he hath to do; on which depends his Care in reference to</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Incampments, or Lodgings, Marches, Ingagements, Sieges, <hi>which are a mixture of</hi> Incamping and Ingaging.</head>
               <p>All which fall to be ſpoken of in the next Place in their Order. And Firſt</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:152881:94"/>
               <head>Of Incampments or Lodgings, of which there are three ſorts.</head>
               <p>THE Firſt is when an Army is on the Wing, waiting every moment for Orders to march.</p>
               <p>The Second is when an Army hath ſurrounded a Place in order to a Siege.</p>
               <p>The Third Incampment is when the Army is in Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of an Enemy, and ſo obliged to regulate its Motions with Caution; then where Nature is found defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, Art ſhould ſupply by caſting up proper Works for Security.</p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:152881:95"/>
               <p>To which end he is to have in his Eye not only the Place where he is to Incamp, or Lodge, but alſo to conſider the number of his Enemies with reference to his own, and to regulate his Motions to <hi>Offend</hi> and <hi>Defend;</hi> ſo that in Incampments or Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he muſt have a regard to the Situation of Ground, whether Mountainous, Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, or repleniſhed with Villages: It is not always in the choice of a General to incamp where he deſires, but is neceſſitated to take ſuch Meaſures as preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances will permit, though he aims at the being Maſter of riſing Grounds, and to have the Benefit of Water and Wood, and if poſſible of all narrow Acceſſes ſituated near
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:152881:95"/>him, and accordingly he cauſes Intrenchments. A Champion Country is much more to be deſired, than to have the Army diſperſed in Villages, being more health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and leſs expoſed to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions and Surprizes, and thereby better capacitated through the means of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments, to Offend and Defend. Alſo Incampments ſhould be choſen for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of conveying Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies; for Obſtructions on ſuch Occaſions have cauſed the Ruin of great Bodies, and occaſioned unſeaſonable Decampments, and ſo given that Victory to thoſe, which otherwiſe might have leaſt expected it, had the Paſſages been open and free.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:152881:96"/>
               <head>Of Marches.</head>
               <p>HERE is Secrecy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, whether it be to ſurpriſe an Army, a Party, or Place, or that it be to prevent being ſurpriſed in Marching, to which Speed, Diligence and Secrecy is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended; for the being out-done, or the out-doing an Enemy in Marches, may prove the unhinging of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs for that Campaign to the one or the other, and ſometimes proves the loſs of advanced Troops, or of the Rear; and many ill Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences attend ſuch whoſe Unhappineſs it hath been to be ſurpriſed. All Marches
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:152881:96"/>are regulated according to the Country, either in order of Battel, or in different Bodies; and if they cannot come to their appointed Place by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ways to lodge in one Body, then they are to lodge as they march, for ſometimes Rivers and Hills, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inconveniences of Ground, may cauſe a greater Compaſs to be made, than deſired, ſo no expreſs Rules can be given: Therefore Care is to be had in Marching for the Preſervation of the Men, and Safety of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery and Carriages, and to be armed againſt any Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. It may be ſometimes adviſable to take different Roads; and if Decampments are made in the ſight of the Enemy, then ſecure the Out-Quarters
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:152881:97"/>to prevent being ſurpriſed; and though the Enemy were diſtant, yet Caution and Diligence is to be uſed according to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the way the Army marches as if he were at hand; for the manner of Marches varies according to the Places through which they are to paſs, with reſpect to the Enemies diſtance, and number of Carriages, no Rules can be given, ſuch are the numerous intervening Accidents; though ſome have laid down Methods for all ſorts of Marches, yet none can be tied up to them, ſo that they are increaſed or diminiſhed as may beſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the ends of ſecuring the whole. Alſo by Marches and Counter-marches, there
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:152881:97"/>may accrue to the General as much Honour, as if he had gained a Victory, for an Enemy may thereby be baffled without Fighting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Ingagements.</head>
               <p>THE Gain or Loſs of a Battel is of the greateſt Conſequence, and is attended with ſuch various Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that it is hard to ſay any thing where ſo many Accidents may change the Scene, and call for new Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods.</p>
               <p>Ingagements are not to be undertaken without the greateſt Conſideration, and that there be a Neceſſity drawn from Reaſon to defend
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:152881:98"/>or aſſault; the wiſe Captain will be always armed againſt Accidents, and if poſſible will ſecure ſuch Ground as may beſt ſute his Number of Horſe and Foot, with the Advantages of being Maſter of Rivers, Woods, narrow Paſſes, riſing Grounds; and if the Wind and Sun will fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Cauſe, it is ſo much the better. He will alſo have regard to the manner and form of Battel, and to the times of Ingagings whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Night or Day, good or bad Weather, and that with reſpect to the Place; alſo the Numbers and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Enemy, with their manner of Practiſe.</p>
               <p>But ſeeing nothing contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes more to a Conqueſt than Stratagems, therefore
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:152881:98"/>good Intelligence is neceſſary, and Spies uſeful, that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries may be made of their Affairs and Motions, as the manner of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campments, their Numbers, Intentions, Supplies; alſo ſetting active Spirits a-work to diſperſe Reports and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Diſorders, may be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: No Mony is better imployed than what is ſpent on Spies and Guides, for by their Intelligence Meaſures are taken; and accordingly Horſe and Foot are diſpoſed ſo that they may beſt ſuccour each other: To effect which, a Foreſight and Preſence of Mind, with an Eye every where, is requiſite to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Affairs for the Benefit and Security of the Army, which ought more to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:152881:99"/>than to offend an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by deſtructive Meaſures; a Fault of which ſome great Men have been guilty, not caring ſo they did but attain their Ends how dearly it was purchaſed, nor how many periſhed, ſo the Victory were but obtained.</p>
               <p>What need more be ſaid than that, whether there be occaſion for retiring or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, there is always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Virtue, Induſtry and Courage, never to appear but with ſuch Reſolution as may give Hopes though in the midſt of Diſpair? A regard alſo is to be had to the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, and Purſued, of the Captives and Wounded, as well Enemies as Friends, for Mercy and good Quarters ſhould ever be the Portion of the Unhappy.</p>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:152881:99"/>
               <p>After the Ingagement is over, Thanks ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by both Parties; for the greateſt Sufferers may find Matter of Thanks, that Things are not worſe, and that they are left Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Mercy at a time when Death reigned ſo, that perhaps there mighc not have been left living ſufficient to bury their Dead, which makes the return of Praiſe more reaſonable in thoſe that remain living.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:152881:100"/>
               <head>As to Sieges, they are a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Incamping and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging.</head>
               <p>TOWNS as well as Perſons have a Fate that hangs over them; for as there is none which firſt or laſt have not been more or leſs beſieged with Humane Infirmities incident to them, ſo there are few Towns that ever eſcaped the Fate of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſieged, though Time may have worn out the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory thereof. Such Deſigns ought to be carried on with Secreſie, and feigned Marches and Counter-marches, amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Enemy by giving a
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:152881:100"/>Jealouſie to adjacent Places, as if the Storm were to fall on them each in particular, that through Incertainties, not knowing where the Storm will fall, they may be obliged to divide their Forces, which may give opportunity to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize the Enemy, when they ſhall not know where to ſend Supplies. After hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſecured the Avenues, then with Diligence proceed to Action, for the ſudden ſetting down before a Place gives Terror; which being invirioned, then Egreſs and Regreſs is to be prevented, and the Camp is to be ſecured by Lines of Circumvalla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Countervallation, which are a Shelter from the Enemies Sallies, and from Attacks from without. Alſo
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:152881:101"/>Proviſions are to be ſecured coming to the Camp, which cannot well be effected if the Beſiegers be not Maſters of the Field.</p>
               <p>Early Information is to be had of the Situation of the Place, how Manned, and ſtored, and of its various ſort of Works and Avenues, with the manner how the Ground and Rivers lie, that Approaches may be Regular, and the Enemies prevented being relieved; that Heights be ſecured that the Camp be not annoyed. Alſo Portable Bridges are to be provided for paſſing Rivers, and to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate Communication. The chief Commander being vers'd in the Inginier's Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, can the better ſatisfie himſelf in all Advances made,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:152881:101"/>whether of Approaches, Lodgments and Works, of what Nature ſoever. As to Mines, though neceſſary, yet are they to be ſuſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cted, for Countermines make them perilous, and often prove the Grave of thoſe who deſigned them for their Enemies De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. That Labour in that kind may not be loſt, Care ought to be taken to diſpoſe them ſo, that inſtead of being a Service, they may not prove a Prejudice to the Enterpriſer. In all reſpects Precaution is neceſſary, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to carry on a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Siege, or a lingering one by Blocade.</p>
               <p>Believing our Commander accompliſhed, and that his Merit, not Character of Great only placed him in that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:152881:102"/>of Truſt, and that he hath more eſſential Virtues to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend him than barely his Birth, ſo needs no Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations as to Particulars, for Methods daily vary according to Place and Times, new Meaſtures are taken, ſo that expreſs Directions cannot be given. And every Age im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves, and new Diſcoveries are made, that what may be adviſable at this Day, may be laid aſide in time to come; general Ideas are only here given. What follows to be ſpoke of is of defending Places when attacked.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:152881:102"/>
               <head>Of defending Places.</head>
               <p>THERE is no Place impregnable; for as was replied by a Warlike Prince, to one who boaſted of the Strength of a Fortified Town, <hi>That he never queſtioned Succeſs if open at the top.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays may be made, and by Courage and Reſolution Time may be prolonged; but when an Army comes armed with Reſolution and Strength, the ſtrongeſt Place at laſt muſt yield; though many times Providence hath fruſtrated Intentions from the lateneſs of the Year, the coldneſs or wetneſs of the Seaſon, and from unforeſeen Wants or
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:152881:103"/>ſurpriſing Accidents. Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity hath taught Men the Art of Fortification, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the defects of Nature by additional Works, which Art hath from Time to Time improved; and though no Place can be made impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet Fortified Garriſons are Hindrances to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of an Enemy.</p>
               <p>Seeing Bulworks are thus neceſſary to Frontiers, and rubs in an Enemies way, which amuſe while Time is gained: Therefore Fortified Places ſhould be timely ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with Neceſſaries, and ſuch Governors as have Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications for their Truſt, of known Fidelity and Merit. Favour and Affection ought not to take place in ſuch Caſes; a Soveraign may be
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:152881:103"/>deceived by a Favourite's Recommendation, who for Mony, or Affection to his Friends, may introduce unfit Objects, who as they bought their Truſt with Mony, may ſell the Place for the ſame Mettal; ſometimes a Mule loaden with Gold hath taken ſuch Fortreſſes, that have been reckoned amongſt the number of impregnable ones. The Soveraign's own Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the Governor ought to take place, he ſhould be induced therefrom to make his Choice, for without Treachery Gariſons are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently expoſed to Accidents; the Men may be wearied, ſpent, and ſick, through over hard Duty. Alſo Magazines may be blown up, and Want may reign, that Friends
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:152881:104"/>within may become a part of the Danger, as well as the Enemies from without.</p>
               <p>Another Inconveniency is that Princes are often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and made believe that Places are better ſtored than they really are; therefore Inſpection ſhould be made, that what is intended as a Garranty againſt unforeſeen Accidents, may not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in Luxury and Often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; for ſuch is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality of ſome, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs of others in Truſt, that to gratifie their Vice they will rather have full Bags, than ſee their Prince's Magazines well ſtored; and care not, though the Soldiers be clothed with Rags, and beg for that Bread that their detained Pay would have
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:152881:104"/>given them. But ſome will chuſe rather profuſely to ſpend, than ſupply the Wants of theſe miſerable ones. It is not only Mony that is aimed at, but they exhauſt the very Stores, and Powder, and that on Saint's Days, and at other times of Jollities alſo, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the Conſequence to have Magazines emptied, whether through Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Vanity or Zeal, for ſome Tutelar Saint. But they hope the evil Day may not come in their time.</p>
               <p>To prolong a Siege Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works are neceſſary to keep the Enemy at a diſtance, in which one Man is ſufficient to anſwer ten without. There ſhould be a ſufficient Strength of Horſe and Foot,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:152881:105"/>and proportionably Stores for both, with Requiſits to make new Works, and for repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Breaches. Let frequent Sallies be made, but by a few; it is better than with great Numbers, for it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents Diſorders in retiring. A few reſolute Men in two Hours may deſtroy, what great Numbers cannot repair in many Days. They ſhould be frequent, and at uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Hours; if vigorouſly carried on, they may keep the Enemy at a diſtance. All Fortifications without, and Proviſions within, ſhould be timely effected, that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my may find the Place pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and in good order. Let the uſeful Inhabitants be imployed, and the uſeleſs ſent away; have a Scrutiny
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:152881:105"/>made into all Stores, and let Care be taken that nothing be concealed nor imbezel'd; that the Soldiery be ſpared from working, alloting them their Hours of Reſt, with Incouragements to attack or defend their Works and Breaches.</p>
               <p>When a Governour hath done all poſſible, and that no Succours comes, and that the Garriſon is ſtraightened, and no appearance how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent falling into the Enemy's Hands, having diſcharged his Truſt, it is then his Duty timely to capitulate, as much as it was before to maintain the Place; after which he may with Honour appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Prince, from whom he deſerves Encomiums for his Fidelity and good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:152881:106"/>and for his timely ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, and thoſe that remained with him by a timely Rendition, reſerving himſelf and them for better Fortune, than to be expoſed to be ſacrificed in a Storm by the Enemy.</p>
               <p>Faults in War are irrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, for the Commander hath but that moment of Action to manage, which if let ſlip, or is miſ-implied is not retrievable, therefore he is concerned to conſider what ſort of People he hath to do with, that accordingly he may arm himſelf with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. There are ſome of ſuch hot fiery Spirits, that to ſtand their firſt Brunt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires great Reſolution, which Ardency being allayed, are much eaſilier managed.
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:152881:106"/>Such Furioſo's meeting with Diſcouragements become ſo unſpirited, that they often with their Courage loſe the Honour of the Day; ſuch can hardly if ever be got to rally again; while others more obſtinate will weather their Difficulties, whoſe Courage increaſes by oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and will maintain their Ground, or ſell every Inch at a dear Rate.</p>
               <p>Some Nations have ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd themſelves in making brave Attacks, falling on with Vigour and Gallantry; and others by a perſevering Obſtinacy have ſhewn their Courage ſtanding like Rocks, and bearing the Shock and Storms of the Aſſailants. As ſome have the Reputation for taking Places, ſo others
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:152881:107"/>have ſignaliz'd themſelves in defending them. Alſo there are thoſe which are very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditious in making Incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Inroads, of incredible lengths. Some make ſpeedy Conqueſts, but let them go as ſoon; like the Northern People, who have over-run Nations, yet never eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any Empire; they were great Enterpriſers, but their Government like a Morning-Dew ſoon vaniſhed, and like Thunder and Lightning they gave Terror and Amazement, but was of no continuance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:152881:107"/>
               <head>Of the Artillery, and the Officers belonging thereunto.</head>
               <p>ARtillery in an Army is a great Contributer to Victory, though a Cumber and a Charge, that formerly the World was not acquainted with; but now is become ſo eſſential to the carrying on a War, that no Victory can be expected where it is not; therefore great Proviſions are made of Guns and Powder, whoſe Invention ſurely was borrowed from Lightning and Thunder, both having the ſame effects to give Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and to do Miſchief; but their Noiſe animates the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of thoſe ingaged in Action.</p>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:152881:108"/>
               <p>The Charge is great, for many are the Materials of which an Artillery is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; for beſides Guns of all ſizes, with Powder and Ball, there are Mortars, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tards, Bombs, Grenadoes, and other Ingines of Deſtruction, with Combuſtibles for Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works; all which require Carriages that have their Drivers, and Artificers at hand, as Gunners, Smiths, Carpenters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for breaking Ground, raiſing Batteries, making Trenches and Mines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And with the number of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, there muſt be found Pontons, Ladders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that whatever Accident arrives, there may ber nothing want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Alſo for Subſiſtence there muſt be Grain of all
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:152881:108"/>ſorts for Horſe and Men, with Mills, and Ovens; all which, when together, ſwells to ſo great a Bulk, that this Warlike Retinue alone looks like an Army, and is under the Conduct</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the General of the Artillery.</head>
               <p>WHO ought to be a Man of Quality, having Experience of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Offices and Buſineſs of every one under his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and to know what is neceſſary for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking any Enterprize, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Field, or at Sieges, among the reſt that of the Duty of the Ingenier, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould be verſed in
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:152881:109"/>the Mathematicks, the better to judge of the Merit of thoſe in that Poſt; whether they have Courage as to dare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves; and alſo in Arts, if able to improve For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications, to mend Faults, and to make a true Judgment of Heights, Depths and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and to point accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to the beſt: Advantage; alſo how to make Approaches and Lodgments, and to place and raiſe Batteries, and with ſafety advance his Works.</p>
               <p>It is the General of the Artillery's Care that none be in Poſts, but ſuch as are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to diſcharge them; as alſo, that there be no want of neceſſary Munitions of War, nor Proviſions of any ſort; that Stores be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezel'd nor decayed, but that
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:152881:109"/>timely Recruits be made in all Particulars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Proviſions.</head>
               <p>WIthout Proviſions great Bodies cannot be kept together, who are a continual Conſumption of Stores, whoſe particular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ought to be well known, and additional Allowances made, leſt there be a falling ſhort. That there may be no Waſte, there is a Purveyor appointed who procures alſo Supplies, and appoints pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Places for Stores, with the times when they are to be delivered out; and that he ſee there be a proportionable number of Bakers, who with
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:152881:110"/>all the other Officers relating all the Stores, are under the Command of a</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Commiſſary-General.</head>
               <p>WHO ought to be a Man of Authority, not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, but faithful, vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, and skilled in buying and chuſing the beſt, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing all to the beſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, for the Good, Eaſe, and Conveniency of the Army; and that what is procured may be conveyed under ſafe Convoy: This Care is the more neceſſary, in that the Welfare of an Army depends thereon; for Want deſtroys more than Fatigues, or rang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Battels. Therefore Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:152881:110"/>are made before the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my march; and all Things are to be regulated, that there be no occaſion for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint.</p>
               <p>The ill managing this Truſt may ruin the hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt Enterprize; the Thoughts of finding Supplies on the Place are not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied on, but he is to arm him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the worſt, for the Enemy may have either car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried of or deſtroyed the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. Therefore Magazines are to be diſperſed for the beſt Advantage for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caption of Stores, of which there ſhould be provided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand in the Camp a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Proviſion for a certain time, that Diſappointments may not bring Diſorder. Therefore Supplies ſhould
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:152881:111"/>never move without ſtrong Convoys, who ſhould have their Marches appointed at uncertain times. Alſo Inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is to be taken that there be no Abuſes from the Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor Deliverers of Stores, nor from Sutlers, and that ſuch as are found Offenders in that kind be made publick Examples.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Baggage</head>
               <p>AS the Artillery is a cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſome Body, ſo we may ſay of the Baggage that it is a very troubleſome Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, which in ſome Places exceeds more than in others, and that from the Negligence of thoſe that ſhould ſee Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:152881:111"/>regulated, by reducing the Bulk to a leſs Compaſs.; to effect which, each Soldier with his Arms and Budget ſhould carry ſome Days Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions with him, for thoſe moſt inured to Fatigue are the likelieſt to obtain Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for it is obſervable, that as thoſe who can keep freſh Troops for Action to the laſt, ſo thoſe that can weather Want, and indure Labour longeſt, are likelieſt to obtain the Victory. But where Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs reigns, ſo that every Soldier muſt have his On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanger, what can be expected from ſuch ſlothful Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions? Therefore that looſe Gang that follows Camps ſhould be diſcouraged, for from theſe it is that Effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, Want, and Diſeaſes,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:152881:112"/>are ingender'd. But ſeeing there is ſo great Trouble to preſerve this ſo cumberſome Luggage, and that when loſt is attended with ſo much Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, and is ſo prejudicial, bringing ſuch irremediable Diſorders, therefore it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable, that the Baggage be reduced to as ſmall a Retinue as poſſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Maſter of the Waggons.</head>
               <p>HIS Buſineſs is to take charge of all Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, to order their Marches, to ſee them quartered, and ſupplied with Neceſſaries for Horſe and Man. He ſhould have under his Command Perſons skilled in the Roads,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:152881:112"/>and in driving with ſuch a number of Artificers as may anſwer any Miſadventure that may happen in the way.</p>
               <p>He ought to have been brought up to driving, and himſelf to underſtand the Roads through which he is to paſs. His Buſineſs is to take daily Inſpection into his Crew, and timely to ſupply Defects of both Man and Horſe, and that all be kept in good order.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="208" facs="tcp:152881:113"/>
               <head>Of the Subſervients to the Army; as Aides de Camp, Chaplains, Phyſicians, Chirurgeons, Provoſts, Guides, Spies.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of Aides de Camp.</head>
               <p>THIS is a Poſt for a Gentleman, whoſe Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is to attend the General. He is as an honourable Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger that carrieth his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which are not to be queſtioned. It is requiſite that he have Courage, Wit, and Fidelity, which with the Annex of Prudence, by improving himſelf and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:152881:113"/>faithful, he may procure his Advancement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Chaplains.</head>
               <p>THEY are Spiritual Guides to regulate the Immoralities. As there are Directors for the diſciplining and uſing Arms; ſo each Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment ſhould have its Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to direct them in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and Conduct of good Manners. He ought to be a Man of good Example, one that carrieth in his Front the Character of Virtue, that his very Preſence ſhould be an Awe, and a Reſtraint to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="210" facs="tcp:152881:114"/>
               <head>Of Phyſicians, Apothecaries and Chirurgeons.</head>
               <p>THEY are that to the Body which the Prieſt is to the Soul; for the Health of both they are conſulted, with this difference, the one gives his Moral Lectures in Health, as well as Sickneſs, while the others Buſineſs is only when Sick or Wounded, then they make Applications, and apply their Remedies. Each Regiment ſhould have of theſe a competent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as ſo many Supplements of Health, that none be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; that it be not ſaid, That more die for want of Skill, Means, and due At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:152881:114"/>than by Sword or Shot. Theſe Functions are honourable, and uſeful, and require ſuitable Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; under which Head it may be no Digreſſion to ſay, That it is the Phiſician's Duty to have an Inſpection into the Medicines, that he ſee they be good, and of Quantities ſufficient to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all Contingencies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Spies and Guides.</head>
               <p>THEY are ſo neceſſary that without them the General would be, in the dark, as to what Meaſures he ſhould take in reference to he Enemy. There ought to be many of both ſorts, each
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:152881:115"/>a Stranger to the other; and as one gives Information of the Country, its Ways and Paſſes, ſo the other doth of the Enemies Motions, and Actings, and what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; theſe ought to be incouraged, but their Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence ſhould not much be relied on, for ſometimes falſe Informations and ſham In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are ſpread abroad to amuſe; and though among ſo great a number of Inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſome may be unfaithful, yet Truth may be picked out, and Uſe may be made of their different Informations; what Mony is ſpent on theſe Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſhould never be regreted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:152881:115"/>
               <head>Of the General-Provost.</head>
               <p>IN the Army he is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Juſtice, by him Vice is reſtrained, and the Irregular kept in order: He is both the Informer, and Puniſher of Offences; it is in his Province to regulate the Prices of Goods. He ought to be of an even Temper, unbyaſſed, and one that dares do right without reſpect of Perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="214" facs="tcp:152881:116"/>
               <head>Of an Army.</head>
               <p>IT is a confuſed Chaos of armed Hirelings, a mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing World, whole Buſineſs is to deſtroy; it is their Trade, and the Work which Nature ſeems to have cut them out for. This their ſo boiſterous Imployment hath qualified them with unpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Minds, as well as with rough Bodies, with which they are capacitated to aſſault, defend, and purſue; to carry on which Work there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, with their Strength, perſonal Courage and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
               <p>This unwieldy Bulk is a moſt unſatiable, ravenous
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:152881:116"/>Animal compoſed of Horſe and Foot, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Conduct of a Chief, by whoſe Care it is ſupported by the Uſe of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, with Proviſions for the Mouth, and War, without which Helps this great Bulk would ſoon melt and dwindle to nothing. Therefore the General's Care is to pay, and feed them, and to find them Action. But though they call them Men of Mettle, yet their Subſtance is neither Braſs, Iron, nor Steel, for their Nature calls for a wherewith to ſupport them anſwerable to their Stations, whether Foot or Horſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Courage will droop, and their Spirits will ſink, and die with their hopes. But it is not ſufficient
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:152881:117"/>to care for the Subſiſtence of this unwieldy Body; for it muſt be made uſeful by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and to keep it in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Juſtice muſt be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, without which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion will follow: Which leads us to the next Head, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Military Diſcipline.</head>
               <p>DIſcipline is the Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that binds great Bodies and Societies, ſo that they hang together and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Corporate; the World could not continue without Diſcipline, it being in the Body-Politick as Nerves and Sinews are in the Body-Natural, that makes Bones,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:152881:117"/>Joints and Limbs hang toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thereby uſeful to the whole Man.</p>
               <p>If Diſcipline in Civil So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety is neceſſary, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear much more in reference to Armies, where are aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſuch numbers of the Dregs of Mankind, many of them being ſuch that it ſeems as if the Places where they lived had ſpued them out as Nuſances, even as the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach doth that which offends it; for Armies are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Receptacle of all ſorts, by which Ages from time to time are purged from their ſo vicious Humors. It may therefore then be aſſerted, That to ſuch a Body that is compoſed of ſo many looſe Corn and Chaff, (tho' there may be ſome good Grain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:152881:118"/>them, yet ſeeing that the other makes the moſt numerous part) it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary there ſhould be appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a rigorous Diſcipline, without which inſtead of being uſeful they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Plague, and Ruin of that Country and Place that raiſed them for their Safety. Therefore Military Laws ſhould be kept up, that Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue may be incouraged and recompenſed, and Offenders find examplary Puniſhments; to prevent which Grievance, let the Soldiers be kept in Action, and be inured to the daily Practice of Military Exerciſes, as the ſeveral Motions of their Bodies, the Uſe of their Arms; which ſhould be practiſed by Horſe and Foot, as being eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:152881:118"/>conducible to Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</p>
               <p>It is of abſolute Neceſſity that Soldiers be inured to Labour, for there by Health is preſerved, and Mony not only ſpared, but gotten; let therefore their idle Hours be filled up by Labour, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Fortifications or other Work; it is good in Peace or War to keep them imployed, thereby Wants may be ſupplied, and by often uſing their Arms they are kept from Ruſt: Alſo the Soldier by Labour and Exerciſe, is preſerved from many Evils and Irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſinful Shifts. By Induſtry not only Corporal Puniſhments are prevented, but even Death it ſelf; for when Men are given up to
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:152881:119"/>Idleneſs, it expoſes them to Shame and Extremity. But Labour is a bitter Root, tho' it bear happy Fruit, and hath Salutary Effects, for Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory is more likely to be the Lot of the Laborious, than the Effeminate and Idle; the former hath a right to it from Merit, it being the Portion of the Diligent and Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p>But to proceed further, the inducing Cauſes why ſuch great Bodies are gather'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are either from Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, Ambition, Honour, or Lucre, and ſome through hopes thereby to live uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled licentiouſly, to bridle ſuch, and that Neceſſities may be ſupplied, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities given to gratifie Emulators of Honour, and
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:152881:119"/>that Virtue may not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recompenſed, nor Vice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed. Therefore it is that Military Laws are made, and Obedience injoined, and a ſevere Diſcipline eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, which cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed without the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſinning againſt himſelf, and his own Intereſt, nor can any thing, go well without an obſervance to Order; for on that Hinge Obedience, it is that all the parts of that great Body do move, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which nothing can be effected, and for want of which all would go to Ruin and Confuſion.</p>
               <p>The Benefits of a Military Diſcipline conſiſt in this, in that it injoins the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Laws, prevents Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, gives Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compences
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:152881:120"/>compences to the Deſerving. By the Terror of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted on Offenders it is that they are made to fear, by which means many are ſaved from Shame and Puniſhments; even Death hath thereby been prevented, for Fear, Shame and Death, are Barricades that prevent committing many Evils. But it is not reaſonable that thoſe who have liſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and receive their Prince's Pay, ſhould be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and conformable to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, eſpecially ſince thereby they are intitled to thoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and Incouragements aſſigned as Recompences to Virtue; therefore it is but juſt that thoſe Puniſhments, they draw on themſelves by tranſgreſſing, ſhould be
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:152881:120"/>their Portion for their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits.</p>
               <p>But there are not wanting thoſe, who are poſſeſſed with this Opinion, That in Camps the Laws lie dormant, as if the Sons of <hi>Mars</hi> and Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, were incompatible: They alledge, That Armies, for the generality, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of the Lees of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuch whom the Civil Government hath caſt off as uſeleſs Members, and ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable: But this their Reaſon ſheweth a greater ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for having an eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Government to reſtrain the Vicious, that of uſeleſs they may become profitable Inſtruments, that what the Civil Law could not effect, the Military might produce: Some like Trees in good
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:152881:121"/>Ground are fruitleſs, but when tranſplanted (though to a more hungry Soil) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more beneficial to their Proprietors.</p>
               <p>But in ſo mixt a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude there are always ſome found, who have had a Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of a generous Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are ſuch as will deſpiſe ſordid Preſidents. Herein is the Uſe of Military Diſcipline, in that it reſtrains the Evil from bad Acts, and preſerves the Good from a Degeneracy. Let it not ſeem to be a Digreſſion to inveigh againſt that crying Evil, <hi>Swearing,</hi> that reigns among the Soldiery, and is one of the roaring Crimes in this Age, and calls for Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance: It were well if the Officers would by Example
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:152881:121"/>refrain this ſo unprofitable a Vice, which is the leſs excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable in not having thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements that attend other Sins, as Pleaſure or Profit. But in Swearing there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Honour nor Advantage, nor can there be expected leſs than ſome tremendous Judgment for defying Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and calling for Confuſion to themſelves and others, and that upon every triffling occaſion. What ſhall we ſay? the Murtherer gratifies his Revenge, the Adulterer his Luſt, the Robber his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs; but the Swearer and Curſer ſell their Souls at the cheapeſt rate of all other Sinners.</p>
               <p>But to proceed; ſince Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are the common Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle of Libertines, and the
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:152881:122"/>Place (in the Opinion of moſt) where Vice rides in Triumph, therefore to rectify Diſorders, a ſevere Diſcipline is ſet on foot to puniſh Vice, and incourage Virtue; for every one hath a natural Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity to deſire Good to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to be preſerved from Hurt, who being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of propoſed Rewards for generous Actions, and that a good Demeanor is the way to obtain Honour and Profit, and that thereby the Door is ſhut againſt Penal Inflictions; and as Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors meet with due Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, ſo Virtue finds its Rewards, Thus by theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections they incourage themſelves in doing well, and hereby the Licentious in Armies are reſtrained, and
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:152881:122"/>Recompences made Inciters to Obedience. Therefore ſuch as do well have Marks of Honour aſſigned them, and that with more Reaſon, when the Pay beareth no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Service per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and for conſiderable Nothings they venture their Lives: Therefore that Prince that recompences not Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age ſhewn on perilous Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, may be ſaid to have neither Ears, Eyes, nor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity; much more thoſe that refuſe to give them their ordinary Pay, but inſtead of Praiſe and Money, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence theſe unhappy ones with Hunger and Want, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſerved their turns, ſend them away with diſcouraging Diſappointments. Such Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpects to Merit, may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:152881:123"/>courage their future expoſing themſelves. Alſo others, when they hear of ſuch ill Uſage, will never conſent to liſt themſelves, unleſs drawn in, for who will fetter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſuch Maſters?</p>
               <p>Thoſe deſerve the Epithet of Fools, who for the tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Pleaſures found in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Evil, expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Juſtice; though in Obedience to Laws, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Criminals may be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Regret, yet Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Chaſtiſements muſt be executed without by reſpect, that others thereby may be deterred from Evil.</p>
               <p>Every Man hath a natural Propenſity by which he is byaſſed to his deſired Object, whether Good or Evil, ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly deſerves Rewards
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:152881:123"/>or Puniſhments, as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominating Paſſion ſhall lead them; for to do Good or Evil are ſeparate Acts of the Mind, and are as oppoſite one to the other, as that of looking up or down. It is thus accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to the Choice made, that Puniſhments or Rewards are intailed, though inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſometimes very unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly; yet as thePhyſician orders Phyſick to recover Health, and to preſerve Life, ſo Military Puniſhments, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Nature of the Fault, ought to be appointed for Chaſtiſements, not Slaughters, in managing the which not only the Nature of the Offence, but the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the Perſon are to be conſidered; for with ſome Shame or a private Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primand,
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:152881:124"/>will have a greater Influence to reform ſome, than more ſevere Corrections with others. But ſome are ſo hardened, that they are incorrigible, ſuch are only fit to be made publick Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; to ſpare ſome ſort of Offenders would be a Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Publick, and a ſhewing Mercy to ſuch as ought to be made Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Terrour, which may be a Preſident of fatal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to the Publick; for unſeaſonable Mercies may be reckoned ſinful Gommiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which may occaſion Repentance when the Evil is paſt being retrieved. Peace and War have hitherto been our Subject, let us now ſay ſomething of that which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipates of both, and is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:152881:124"/>which is that called a Truce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Truce.</head>
               <p>A Truce is a Reſpite, or a Ceſſation of Arms li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited for a certain Time, and for divers Ends, as to bury the Dead, or in order to Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some call it a Camp-Peace, or the Armies Holy-day, where Hoſtilities ceaſe, though the War doth not. A Truce between <hi>Turks</hi> and Chriſtians differs only in length of Time, and is in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a Peace, though it carries not the Name.</p>
               <p>But with whom ſoever it is made, it ought to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly obſerved, though it
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:152881:125"/>is beſt to make no Truce at all, it being but to grant a breathing time to an Enemy that is weary, and deſires lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to recruit Strength, to purſue the War with more Vigour. Truce is neither Peace nor War, but partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pates of both, and is as the Intervals between Night and Morning, and Day and Night, ſo it may be called the dawning of the Day, if a Peace ſucceeds. A Truce hath commonly a Pretence to be in order to a Peace, and to promote it is propoſed, though little leſs is intended than to be a Stratagem to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvent. Alſo Experience hath ſhewn, That Fighting by Stratagems hath often had Succeſs, when open Force could not prevail. Thus a
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:152881:125"/>Ceſſation of Arms hath been fatal to thoſe, who by open Force were thought invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; theſe Intervals between Peace and War are not ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable, could they be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſince thereby no Peace is obtained, nor yet is Hoſtility ſuffered. This ſpace of time between Peace and War is more vexatious and uneaſy than War it ſelf, ſo that even Extremities are more to be deſired, than dilatory Truces,</p>
               <p>I queſtion whether it be not better to fall down right, than to hang in ſuſpence? To go on with Reſolution is better than to make a ſtop, ſince a Pauſe may not be leſs dangerous than a Fall; and thoſe that ſeek a Ceſſation do give occaſion to ſuſpect they
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:152881:126"/>are in a miſerable Condition, when reduced to that Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity that they can ſuffer nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Peace nor War.</p>
               <p>In Offenſive and Defenſive War are two oppoſite Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but there is a third ſort that eſpouſes neither Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, but ſtand by as Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, who are call'd Neuters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Neutrality.</head>
               <p>THOSE who will be Neuters will find Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to countenance their Neutrality. Some are influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced from private, and ſome from publick Motives. Alſo Ambition makes ſome Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Coveteouſneſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:152881:126"/>and there are thoſe that from Neceſſity are ſo; and ſome are for blowing the Coals, and cauſe Claſhings between Neighbours, that with the Frog and Mouſe they may by the Bird of Prey be ſeized on with more Eaſe, and ſo reap the End deſigned of profiting by their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, when wearied with Fighting. Thus, as is ſaid, Coveteouſneſs alſo may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Neutrality, having for end to monopolize to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves an uninterrupted Commerce, while their Neighbours are imbroiled; for which Reaſon it may be ſaid, That they feed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by their Neighbour's Hurt.</p>
               <p>It is a moſt unhappy Caſe when Neceſſity compels to a
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:152881:127"/>Neutrality, that like <hi>Janus</hi> they are forced to carry two Faces. It is hard to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced not to know on which Crutch to reſt. They are very unhappy who through Neceſſity are obliged to a Neutrality, for thereby they run a hazard to loſe all, through on over-deſire to keep all Parties, that inſtead of ſecuring a Friend they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail on themſelves a certain Enemy, and become the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Victor's next Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. The Caſe is truly to be lamented when obliged to this hazardous Fate, either to ſink or ſwim with one of the contending Parties, or elſe to be expoſed to be cruſhed for ſtanding by Spectator, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being uſeful to faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate the Conqueror's end.
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:152881:127"/>It may in ſome Caſes be ſaid, That thoſe that are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us are for us; yet it is not always ſo taken, for Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions for Quarrel are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally grounded from denying ſeaſonable Aſſiſtances.</p>
               <p>And the Truth is, Neuters are ſeldom counted otherwiſe than Enemies to both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſince for not ſiding with neither Party they are ſure to have one for Enemy; though their Condition at preſent is ſweet, yet like the Book given to eat was luſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Mouth, but prov'd bitter in the Belly; yet however evenly Neuters may carry it, there will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſecretly ſomething of an Inclination to one ſide more than to the other.</p>
               <pb n="238" facs="tcp:152881:128"/>
               <p>It is to be confeſſed that ſometimes a Prince is obliged in point of Honour to ſtand ſtill, and not aſſiſt thoſe whom, according to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, he may be byaſſed to appear in their Favour; and ſuch may be the Caſe, that Honour and Gratitude hath tyed his Hands ſo, that he cannot but ſtand Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>It concerns thoſe who find themſelves thus hampered to carry evenly, and to uſe Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Temper in ſo tickliſh an Affair, waving all ſecret Tendencies that may be had to one more than to the other, that things be ſo managed that each Party be ſatisfied, and pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with this Belief, that if byaſſed on any ſide, it is of theirs.</p>
               <pb n="239" facs="tcp:152881:128"/>
               <p>To hinder Neutrality is as impoſſible, as it is for ſome to avoid the Shame and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger they incur thereby. There are alſo ſuch that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſtand Spectators, that they may the better ſee which way the Game will go: There are thoſe that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn with an artificial Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mace the Rupture made, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the one as well as the other, as wanting Foreſight and Moderation, though it may be themſelves have been the ſecret Incendiaries: Such Reflections ſurely were the Cauſe that the <hi>Romans</hi> would never allow any to be Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but they muſt either make themſelves declared Friends, or be proclaimed publick Enemies.</p>
               <pb n="240" facs="tcp:152881:129"/>
               <p>It is confeſſed that thoſe that are Neuters, while in that State, ſeem to have the Advantage of the upper and neather Springs to inrich themſelves, while their Neighbours are exhauſting each other; but to hold the Scale ſo even requires Art, and may be of great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, if they can perform offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Favours that are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to one, yet inoffenſive to another, and ſo obliging in Deportment to both, that may give occaſion to ſay, theſe are the Neuters, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſe their Friends, nor procure to themſelves Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="241" facs="tcp:152881:129"/>
               <head>Of <hi>GERMANY;</hi> its Strength and Power.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GErmany</hi> is a vaſt Body compoſed of many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, and repleniſhed with a Warlike, Strong-bodied People: It lies in the Heart of <hi>Europe,</hi> and looks upon the reſt of his Neighbours with Diſdain, as ſo many lopped off Members, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſtart Powers,</hi> its Haughtineſs will not allow a Corrival; though its Fate be ſuch, that it hath for Emulator <hi>France,</hi> between whom great Conteſt hath been for Empire, they being the two moſt tranſcendent Powers of <hi>Europe,</hi> who give Peace or War to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:152881:130"/>and are the two Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivals for Empire, who for Ages have had Conteſts to the alarming all <hi>Europe,</hi> who were glad to take their Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures according to their Riſe, or Fall, ever labouring to ſupport the ſinking State of the Decliner.</p>
               <p>Had <hi>Germany</hi> the ſame Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that attends <hi>France,</hi> of being under one abſolute Sovereign, it needed only its own Strength to ſupport its Grandeur; but where there are many Heads, there the Feet are uneaſy; neither can that Country be rich, where the Commonality is kept at under; which Grievance, if remedied in <hi>Germany,</hi> that Country would be richer, and the People more eaſy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is to be wiſhed, That the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:152881:130"/>of thoſe who labour under ſuch Difficulties, were made more tolerable.</p>
               <p>In times paſt <hi>Germany</hi> was the <hi>Romans</hi> Terror, but ſince the Seat of Empire hath been transferred to that Warlike People, who are the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> Dread, who but for them might long ſince have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run all <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did this great Continent know how its Strength con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the Union of its Parts, it would be no leſs a Terror to <hi>Europe,</hi> than if under one Sovereign; for <hi>Germany</hi> hath all the Advantages for War within it ſelf, beyond any Nation in the World; what in reſpect of its great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Men, Arms, and Horſe, with their long Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:152881:131"/>from many Ages, and natural Diſpoſition to War, that even Nature ſeemeth to have cut them out for that purpoſe, having given them ſtrong brawny Bodies capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to indure Hardſhips; who are alſo bold, couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and fearleſs in Danger. <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> tells us in his 13th Book, Tat no Nation exceeds the <hi>Germans</hi> in War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Exploits, and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Honeſty. They are Lovers of Honour, and have had ſince many Ages, the Character of a moſt Noble and Heroick People. They were <hi>Rome</hi>'s Plague, and gave that Miſtreſs of the World more Diſquiet for many Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies than the <hi>Carthagenians,</hi> or any other of her Enemies.</p>
               <pb n="245" facs="tcp:152881:131"/>
               <p>They have within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Sinews of War, <hi>viz.</hi> Mines of Gold and Silver, and other Minerals, with all neceſſary Munitions for Men and Horſe. And what is moſt admirable is, That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their many Diſcouragements, yet they perſiſt unweariedly in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting their Miſeries, even for thirty Years together, and that in their own Bowels; which had they been united, they might with much more Advantage to themſelves have directed their Strength againſt their common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my the <hi>Turk,</hi> or his Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, though the latter be the more formidable for Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Strength and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. And though upon extraordinary Occasions they
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:152881:132"/>have called to their Aſſiſtance the Northern Crowns, who for that Reaſon may be ſtiled the <hi>Germans</hi> little <hi>Tartars,</hi> yet probably that they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Aſſiſtance, was more Policy, than Neceſſity. For it is not only the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of <hi>Germany,</hi> but the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and their Princes alſo, have at all times been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned for War, having never wanted occaſion to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalize themſelves, either through the Differences that aroſe among themſelves, or from what Work was cut out for them by theſe two formidable Powers the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> between whom they are ſeated; the latter following his Anceſtor's Steps, who ever oppoſed the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Family, as having
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:152881:132"/>a Jealouſy of its Greatneſs, ſo uſed Means to foment a Suſpicion of the Growth of that Power, leſt it ſhould ſwallow all like a common Inundation; for which end, to keep it under, Leagues were contracted with the <hi>Turks.</hi> Thus did <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King enter into League with <hi>Solyman,</hi> and under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to ſave himſelf, he pleaded Neceſſity, ſeeing that the <hi>Netherlands, Spain,</hi> and part of <hi>Italy,</hi> became ſo many Members of its Greatneſs, which were the Pretences with which he varniſhed over his ſo unchriſtian-like Policy of joining with Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, to ſhelter himſelf from a ſuppoſed Danger; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it is this Confederacy, and the Fears thereof, that
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:152881:133"/>have reſtrained <hi>Germany</hi> from putting in execution thoſe great Deſigns it had framed.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Henry</hi> the Son of the ſaid <hi>Francis</hi> followed the ſame Methods, who by ſuch Leagues indeavoured to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the <hi>German</hi> Arms. And this preſent King, though for a different end, doth the ſame; for he knoweth that to keep his Subject's active Spirits buſied abroad, is the way to prevent their looking for Matter to work on at home; for his Subjects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing numerous and poor, and the Nobility many, he finds ways to give them Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by keeping them low, their Fortunes depend on their Sword, and the King's Favour, who having in his Hands the abſolute
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:152881:133"/>Government of Perſons, and diſpoſal of Eſtates, he is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitated thereby arbitrarily to take ſuch Meaſures as may beſt anſwer his Ends; and having theſe Advantages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his Neighbours, it is no wonder that his Dominions and Power is increaſed as it is at this Day, which has given him occaſion to let the World know the Native and Intrinſick Strength of <hi>France,</hi> which till this King's Reign was not known, no not to it ſelf.</p>
               <p>But what Satisfaction and Honour can oppreſſed Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have to ſee their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Slaves is increaſed? Can Conqueſts be due, where Acqueſts are made by Breach of Faith? Surely thoſe
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:152881:134"/>Countries that are taken ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimately, ought to have another Name given them than that of Conqueſts. It may be ſaid of ſome, That they are to <hi>Europe,</hi> what <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal</hi> was once ſaid to be to <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi> to <hi>Carthage,</hi> that they were their Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and Scourge.</p>
               <p>It is to be lamented, That Chriſtians cannot be content with thoſe Boundaries that God and Nature ſeems to have aſſigned them, but they muſt make Incroachments. Is not the <hi>Turk</hi> an Enemy ſufficient to bandy againſt? but that there muſt be found out Pretences to cloak ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Ends, to join in Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy with him. It were to be deſired rather, that all
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:152881:134"/>Chriſtian Powers would join as <hi>One</hi> againſt that ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy the <hi>Turk,</hi> of whom it may be ſaid with much more Juſtice what was ſpoke of <hi>Antony,</hi> That he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to Mangle, Murther, and Wallow in the Blood of <hi>Innocents.</hi> How can Chriſtian Princes ſo long indure that Power to reign, that holds their Chriſtian Brethren in the Chains of Servitude? Would <hi>France</hi> join in this ſo good a Work, or at leaſt ſtand Neuter, the Controverſy would ſoon be decided; but that great Prince is ſo intent on the accumulating Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies of Honour, and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandizing his Fame and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, that there ſeems not room left for any other
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:152881:135"/>Thoughts to take place, than what tends to the gratifying that his ſo aſpiring a Paſſion for Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="253" facs="tcp:152881:135"/>
               <head>MAXIMS.</head>
               <p>NOne without juſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, and Reaſons drawn from a good Cauſe, ſhould enter into open Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility.</p>
               <p>To ſeek Peace by War, is like Angling for Fiſh with a golden Hook.</p>
               <p>When-Ambition is the Foundation of War, Succeſs may be doubted.</p>
               <p>Thoſe neceſſitated to defend themſelves, may more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably expect Succeſs than the Aggreſſor.</p>
               <p>Haſty Enterprizes are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of at leiſure.</p>
               <pb n="254" facs="tcp:152881:136"/>
               <p>A General hath not only to contend with Men, but with Contingencies, as Want, Hunger, and Diſcontent, which are Enemies hardly to be vanquiſhed.</p>
               <p>It is ſafer to build on pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Meaſures, than on For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
               <p>He that hazards leaſt, plays the ſafeſt Game.</p>
               <p>It is better to defend a Country by Juſtice, than to conquer one by Force.</p>
               <p>By Circumſpection in Peace the Diſaſters of War may be eſcaped.</p>
               <p>The nobleſt Conqueſt is where Love and good Offices obtain the Victory.</p>
               <p>He conquers that doth good Offices, and thoſe are van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed which receive them.</p>
               <pb n="255" facs="tcp:152881:136"/>
               <p>He that defends his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try by the Sword deſerves Honour, but he that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains it in Peace deſerves more.</p>
               <p>Good Counſel and Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence is ſometimes of more uſe than Arms.</p>
               <p>War ſeldom anſwers the propoſed end.</p>
               <p>Purchaſe Peace with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, rather than acquire it by a long War.</p>
               <p>An Enemy is not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned.</p>
               <p>The Conqueror ought not to refuſe Propoſals of Peace.</p>
               <p>Enemies ought not to be ſlighted, tho' few in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p>Contempt had of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Strength or Merit, ſhould not cauſe Security.</p>
               <pb n="256" facs="tcp:152881:137"/>
               <p>Tho' an Enemy be weak in Power, yet is he not to be undervalued, for an anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Atome may incommode the ſtouteſt Man.</p>
               <p>A deſperate Enemy is not eaſily beaten.</p>
               <p>Enemies in Deſpair are to be feared, though they are inferiour in number.</p>
               <p>Neceſſity hath no Law; when compelled to Action to ſtand deliberating then is out of doors, there being only a Preſence of Mind required, which being backed with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, the Undaunted, in the midſt of Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, doth dare boldly aſpire to Victory.</p>
               <p>Diſgrace is augmented if overcome by a leſſened Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and no Honour is gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch a Victory; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:152881:137"/>deſpiſe not an Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, leaſt you increaſe your Shame if overcome by him, or loſe that Honour which might have been gained by Conqueſt; which are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Conſequences.</p>
               <p>Know an Enemy before thou deſpiſe him.</p>
               <p>He that feareth not an Enemy knows not what War is.</p>
               <p>Prudence is neceſſary in undertaking, and Reſolution in execution.</p>
               <p>Preparations ſecure a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace, and make way for Victory.</p>
               <p>Never uſe Arms where you can conquer with Money.</p>
               <p>Overcome your Enemy by Policy rather than Fight.</p>
               <p>When an Enemy cannot be oppoſed, then tolerable
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:152881:138"/>Conditions of Peace are wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
               <p>To penetrate the Deſigns of an Enemy is a Mark of a piercing Capacity, but to conceal our own is to excell in Prudence.</p>
               <p>Wiſe Parlies do ſometimes more than armed Forces.</p>
               <p>He that will not hear Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is not fit to reign.</p>
               <p>That Prince deſerves to reign long, whoſe good Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons exceed his Works.</p>
               <p>He that hath no Friend, cannot be ſaid to reign.</p>
               <p>Vice make Princes odious, when the meaneſt Man is made honourable by Virtue.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that excell not in Virtue, deſerve not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
               <p>Good Actions recommend more than Riches.</p>
               <pb n="259" facs="tcp:152881:138"/>
               <p>Examples of Virtue are of greater efficacy than Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
               <p>A good Opinion is of more uſe than Riches.</p>
               <p>He that will be eſteemed muſt always do well.</p>
               <p>A Kingdom may be thought invincible, when Immoralities are baniſhed.</p>
               <p>A Prince ought to be armed againſt all Accidents.</p>
               <p>One may begin a War, but the Victorious only can end it.</p>
               <p>A prudent Jealouſie is a commendable Qualification, the exceſs is of ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               <p>That Prince may do what he pleaſes, when he wills no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what he ought.</p>
               <p>That Prince that compaſſes his ends by Treaty, deſerves
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:152881:139"/>more Honour than he that overcomes by Battel.</p>
               <p>Where a Prince hath loſt his Authority, there Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot be expected.</p>
               <p>Revenge is not laudable in a Chief, and often is the cauſe of fatal Conſequences.</p>
               <p>A good Prince makes good Subjects.</p>
               <p>A Friend in an Enemies Council, is more advantagious than thouſands in the Field.</p>
               <p>All Conteſts, like Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices Eggs, are to be cruſh'd in the Shell.</p>
               <p>Opprobrious Words may incenſe, but not beat an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
               <p>Let a Door be open for a deſperate Enemy to enter, either by Compoſition or Quarter.</p>
               <pb n="261" facs="tcp:152881:139"/>
               <p>Severity as well as Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are prejudicial, and may excite Rebellion.</p>
               <p>Enemies are not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, nor triumph'd over.</p>
               <p>Let your Enemies arming cauſe you to arm.</p>
               <p>Uſe as Friends thoſe you would make yours, for Fire and Sword doth but quicken Reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Some profit by Differences fomented among Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Princes.</p>
               <p>Small Shrubs by bending weather a Storm, when great ſturdy Oaks are torn up by the Roots.</p>
               <p>There is neither Prudence nor Profit in being of too open a Conduct.</p>
               <p>Great Souls, like Rocks, are immoveable.</p>
               <pb n="262" facs="tcp:152881:140"/>
               <p>There is no Policy in hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more Enemies than one at once.</p>
               <p>Expoſe not to hazard more than what cannot be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Right Intelligence is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, as well in reference to ones own, as the Enemies Strength.</p>
               <p>Set a good Face on a bad Matter, in the greateſt Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies ſhew Courage and Conſtancy.</p>
               <p>To be firſt ready is advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious.</p>
               <p>Ambition and Coveteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs break Leagues and awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken War.</p>
               <p>Fortune ſporteth it ſelf in making great little, and little great.</p>
               <p>To boaſt over an Enemy is inſulting, and provokes to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
               <pb n="263" facs="tcp:152881:140"/>
               <p>Where Want reigns, no Diſcipline is obſerved.</p>
               <p>The Commonalty is more prompt to Rebellion, than Battel; and apter to Talk, than Fight.</p>
               <p>It is the Bane of Armies when Quality, and not Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are the Foundation of Preferment.</p>
               <p>Truſt not where you have been deceived.</p>
               <p>It is needleſs to declare War againſt thoſe prone to it from former Succeſſes.</p>
               <p>Breakers of honeſt Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracies deſerve Cenſure.</p>
               <p>He is in the wrong that gives the Cauſe of War, not he that ſeeks Redreſs.</p>
               <p>Delays in Danger are the Mother of inſuing Evils.</p>
               <p>Failings of Superiours make
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:152881:141"/>them in the Eyes of Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours contemptible.</p>
               <p>Well-weigh'd Counſel ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom fails.</p>
               <p>There is a happy Minute more worth, than all the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies of War.</p>
               <p>Fortune is no where ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, as in War.</p>
               <p>One Hours Diſtaſter may overthrow the Honour got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ruin future Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations.</p>
               <p>Faults in War are irrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>Though Money be the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news of War, yet by Science, Prudence, and Perſonal Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, Victory is obtained.</p>
               <p>Succeſs is not to be expected where Money is ſcant, and Enemies abound.</p>
               <p>He that gets by Conqueſt
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:152881:141"/>doth much, but he that can keep what he hath gotten doth more.</p>
               <p>Numbers are little avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able where Fear reigns.</p>
               <p>The Captain's end ſhould be Glory, not to be a Scourge, ſeeking by Conqueſt to build up, not to confound.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are unfaithful to their own Intereſt, will not be true to anothers.</p>
               <p>Awe makes Tyrants obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Love Soveraigns.</p>
               <p>Many Things are loſt for not being attempted.</p>
               <p>Courage and Courteſie are great Ornaments to a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
               <p>As Rewards are neceſſary, ſo are Chaſtiſements.</p>
               <p>A Captain ought to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, watchful, and of a reſolute Spirit; wiſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:152881:142"/>liberal to reward, and valiant to defend.</p>
               <p>Happy is that Country where Men of Merit are not diſcouraged, and where Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are not ill placed.</p>
               <p>It is Valour's Badge neither to fear, nor to be too confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
               <p>Fortune never waits on the Fearful.</p>
               <p>Fear ſtifles generous Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings in their birth.</p>
               <p>Fear is honourable when it proceeds not from a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Concern, but for the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the whole.</p>
               <p>Tameneſs in Officers is a Diſcouragement, and cauſes Deſerters.</p>
               <p>Nothing unarms a People like Effeminacy, Luſt, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and Idleneſs.</p>
               <pb n="267" facs="tcp:152881:142"/>
               <p>Fortune and Prudence are uſually Companions.</p>
               <p>He that is feared by many, hath reaſon to fear many.</p>
               <p>He hurts the Good that ſpares the Ill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Though a Wound may be cured, yet the Scar remains.</p>
               <p>No Danger is overcome without Danger.</p>
               <p>Deſpair ſets on edge Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and makes Cowards va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant, and ſpirits them in Combat.</p>
               <p>The Effects of Deſpair are ſurpriſing, and have the ſame product which true Courage hath in others.</p>
               <p>Great Souls are capable of great Things; and if Power be annexed, then may be reaſonably expected great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances.</p>
               <pb n="268" facs="tcp:152881:143"/>
               <p>The Soldier ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be daring, and bold, but have alſo a Faculty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving; for Invention is as neceſſary as Valour.</p>
               <p>It is not ſafe to Disband Forces, while the Enemies are on foot.</p>
               <p>When an Enemy is ſecure, then attack him.</p>
               <p>Let the Intelligence of your Enemies Motions be at hand, tho' they be far off.</p>
               <p>Early inure an Army to Hardſhips, before Neceſſity reduces them to it.</p>
               <p>Let Courage increaſe with Danger; for by loſing the one, you hazard all.</p>
               <p>It is neceſſary in Officers to have a natural Propenſity to great Actions.</p>
               <p>To ſtand the Enemies firſt Fury is the way to overcome.</p>
               <pb n="269" facs="tcp:152881:143"/>
               <p>Fortreſſes ſhould be Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries to undiſciplined Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
               <p>The more Enemies the more Honour.</p>
               <p>Cowards have Lyons Mouths, but Hearts like Hares.</p>
               <p>A prudent Retreat is as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable as a Victory.</p>
               <p>Spend not time in Plunder till the Work is done.</p>
               <p>The Generous will not be diſcouraged, tho' their Merit meets not with due Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe.</p>
               <p>He deſerves not the Name of Victor, that conquers baſely.</p>
               <p>Generoſity is never ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, as when exerciſed towards an Enemy.</p>
               <p>Victory moderated by Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, is ſplendid and ſafe.</p>
               <pb n="270" facs="tcp:152881:144"/>
               <p>The falling on the Spoil hath often been the Bane of Armies.</p>
               <p>To be ſedate in a Hurry, and calm in Confuſion, to preſerve a Preſence of Mind in the greateſt Exigencies, are neceſſary Requiſits in a General.</p>
               <p>Diſciplined Soldiers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good Officers, will not anſwer the end.</p>
               <p>Temerity is ſeldom ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful; but upon neceſſity Boldneſs exceeds Counſel.</p>
               <p>Incounter not Enemies in their height of Fury.</p>
               <p>Thoſe have gained Honour from the want of Courage in an Adverſary, that elſe would have had Diſgrace.</p>
               <p>Ill uſe is made of Victory when none is ſpared.</p>
               <pb n="271" facs="tcp:152881:144"/>
               <p>Old <hi>Veteran</hi> Troops ought not to be choſen for deſperate Enterprizes, but young Years, and boiling Youth, who have no Thought but that of Succeſs and Glory.</p>
               <p>He that hath moſt Courage is leaſt cruel.</p>
               <p>Private Men ſhould have publick Marks of Honour, as a Preſident to incite others to deſire that their Heads may be crown'd with ſuch Laurels.</p>
               <p>There may be as great Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty in ſparing all, as to ſpare none.</p>
               <p>Victory ſhould not thirſt after Blood, nor be cruel to obtain it.</p>
               <p>What Power and Policy cannot bring about, Gold may effect.</p>
               <pb n="272" facs="tcp:152881:145"/>
               <p>The Queſtion ought rather to be where the Enemies are, than how many, leaſt it give to think that Fear, rather than Valour, made the Query.</p>
               <p>The Sword diſpatches quickly, but Fear ſtrikes down like Thunder.</p>
               <p>He is ſooneſt hurt, who feareth moſt.</p>
               <p>Great Souls, in glorious Enterpriſes, have no ſenſe of Danger.</p>
               <p>The more Danger the more Glory.</p>
               <p>The Foundation of Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Knowledge ſhould be laid even from Youth.</p>
               <p>The time for Battel is, when Men are moſt ſpirited for Action.</p>
               <p>An Army kept idle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generates, and are trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:152881:145"/>Gueſts where quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Never be confident of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, nor yet deſpair of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
               <p>Inteſtine Animoſities ruin the greateſt Bodies.</p>
               <p>Aim at Numbers, but truſt not in them.</p>
               <p>Courage makes all Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes eaſy.</p>
               <p>Delays may turn the Scales, ſo that the Conqueror may become the Conquered.</p>
               <p>It is an unprofitable Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory that is obtained by the Ruin of ones own Country.</p>
               <p>That Victory is not perfect where the Heart is not made Captive as well as the Body.</p>
               <p>To overcome by Clemency is more honourable, than to ſubdue by the Sword.</p>
               <pb n="274" facs="tcp:152881:146"/>
               <p>Courage is ſhown more in the choice to die free, than to ſuffer a languiſhing Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in an Enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <p>An unlimited Power is of great uſe to capacitate the General to do great Things, which he that waits for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders cannot effect.</p>
               <p>There is Incouragement to attempt a Siege, when the Governour is known to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being corrupted.</p>
               <p>The Knowledge of a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons being over-ſtored, may as ſoon draw on a Siege, as when its Wants are diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
               <p>Palliate Diſgraces, and call Flights Retreats.</p>
               <p>Let Spies be rather your Enemies Subjects than your own.</p>
               <pb n="275" facs="tcp:152881:146"/>
               <p>Spies are the Generals Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets which are gained by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and preſerved by Hope.</p>
               <p>Fortified Places, Armies and Fleets, are vain Things, when God lends not a Hand.</p>
               <p>Perjury calls for Judgment, but more eminently when found in Princes.</p>
               <p>He that can turn Revenge into Mercy, and Hatred into Love, is Praiſe-worthy.</p>
               <p>A mean ſpirited Prince is rather the Object of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt than Fear.</p>
               <p>Religion is the uſual Cloak for Rebellion.</p>
               <p>Furious Spirits are ſeldom appeaſed by ſoft Words, nor Submiſſions.</p>
               <p>It is beſt for Princes to judge only according to Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:152881:147"/>to do nothing but what is expedient, and labour not ſo much to ſhew their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as their Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Vindicative Spirits are their own Tormenters.</p>
               <p>No Game is too great for Lookers on, ſay Neuters.</p>
               <p>Greatneſs and Care are Twins.</p>
               <p>Soveraigns are Judges here, yet they are judged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and arraigned at the Tribunal of every private Mans Cenſure.</p>
               <p>Though Soveraigns are Gods on Earth, yet they ſee and hear with others Eyes, and Ears, and are obliged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to take Meaſures.</p>
               <p>The Wiſe proceed to Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Caution, but the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>experienced are raſh in their Enterprizes.</p>
               <pb n="277" facs="tcp:152881:147"/>
               <p>Sometimes Temerity is of more Uſe, and a greater Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, than more prudent Meaſures.</p>
               <p>The General's Staff is an Ornament, but it loads as well as it adorns.</p>
               <p>The Enemies Quarters are eaſilier beat up and ſurprized, when their Diſtances have made them ſecure.</p>
               <p>Let Ambuſhes be a Secret, leaſt the being circumvented make deſigned for the place of Victory.</p>
               <p>The Wiſe never wonder, nor are ſurprized, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing happens to them, but what they expected, and are armed for its reception.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:148"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:148"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and ſold by <hi>John Jones,</hi> at the <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</head>
            <p>POpery, Superſtition, Ignorance and Knavery, very unjuſtly by a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the General pretended; but as far as was Charg'd, very fully proved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Diſſenters that were concerned in the <hi>Surey</hi> Impoſter. By <hi>Zach. Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Surey</hi> Impoſtor: Being an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a late Fanatical Pamphlet, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Surey Demoniack.</hi> By <hi>Zach. Taylor,</hi> A. M. and One of the King's Preachers for the County-<hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon of Good Works. Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Feckenham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> on <hi>Thurſday</hi> in <hi>Whitſun-week, May</hi> 17, 1697. at the Yearly Meeting of the Feofees, appointed by Sir <hi>Thomas Cooks</hi> Baronet, to manage the Charity
<pb facs="tcp:152881:149"/>given by him, for Educating and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for Twelve poor Children there, and for Maintaining a School-maſter to Inſtruct them in Learning and Piety. By <hi>John Jepthcott,</hi> D. D. Prebendary of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and Rector of <hi>All Saints</hi> in the Burrought of <hi>Eveſham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A View of the Diſſertation upon the Epiſtles of <hi>Phalaris, Themiſtocles,</hi> &amp;c. Lately publiſh'd by the Reveren'd Dr. <hi>Bentley.</hi> Alſo of the Examination of that Diſſertation by the Honourable Mr. <hi>Boyle.</hi> In order to the Manifeſting the Incertitude of Heathen Chronology.</p>
            <p>Eight Chirurgical Treatiſes, on theſe following Heads, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. of Tumours. 2. Of Ulcers. 3. Of Diſeaſes of the <hi>Anus.</hi> 4. Of the King's Evil. 5. Of Wounds. 6. Of Gun-ſhot Wounds. 7. Of Fractures and Luxations. Of the <hi>Lues Venera.</hi> By <hi>Richard Wiſeman,</hi> Serjeant-Chirurgeon to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second. The Third Edition. Fol.</p>
            <p>The General Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, from the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Accounts of Time, to the Reign of his preſent Majeſty King <hi>William</hi> III. Taken from the moſt ancient Records, Manuſcripts, and printed Hiſtorians, with Memorials of the moſt eminent
<pb facs="tcp:152881:149"/>Perſons in Church and State; as alſo, the Foundations of the moſt noted Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries and both Univerſities. Vol. I. By <hi>James Tyrrell,</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Fol.</p>
            <p>Treatiſes upon ſeveral Subjects, <hi>viz.</hi> Reaſon and Religion, or the Grounds and Meaſures of Devotion. Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon the Conduct of Humane Life. The Charge of Schiſm continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Two Treatiſes concerning Divine Light. Spirituall Counſel, or, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Advice to his Children. Written by <hi>John Norris,</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merton</hi> near <hi>Sarum.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>Practical Diſcourſes upon ſeveral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subjects, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Religious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in common Converſation. Of the Fear of Death. Concerning the Extent of Chriſt's Satisfaction. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning practical Atheiſm. Of walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Faith. Concerning Charity to the Poor. Concerning the right Uſe of the World. Concerning the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Vanity of Humane Life.—An Admonition concerning two late Books, called, <hi>A Diſcourſe of the Love of God.</hi> Vol. IV. Written by <hi>John Norris,</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Bemerton</hi> near <hi>Sarum.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:150"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ars Chirurgica,</hi> or a Compendium of the Theory and Practice of <hi>Chyrurgery,</hi> in Seven Books. Containing, 1. The Inſtruments and Operations of the Art. 2. The Removal of Defilements. 3. The Cure of Tumours. 4. The Cure of Wounds. 5. The Cure of Ulcers. 6. The Cure of Fractures. 7. The Cure of Diſlocations. Shewing the Names, Cauſes, Signs, Differences, Prognoſticks, and various Intentions of Curing all kind of Chirurgick Diſeaſes, from Head to Foot, happening to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Bodies. To which is added, <hi>Pharmacopoeia Chyrurgica,</hi> or, The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Store, in Latin and Engliſh; which contains an abſolute Sett of choice Preparations or Medicaments, fitted for the compleat and univerſal Practice both of <hi>Phyſick</hi> and <hi>Chyrurgery.</hi> The whole Work <hi>Galenically</hi> and <hi>Chymically</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; the like yet never publiſhed in any Language whatſoever. By <hi>William Salmon,</hi> M. D. living at the Great Houſe by <hi>Black-Friers-Stairs, London.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>Poems upon ſeveral Occaſions. By <hi>Daniel Baker,</hi> M. A. ſometimes of <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and <hi>Caius</hi> College in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:150"/>
            <p>Reform'd Devotions in Meditations, Hymns and Petitions, for every Day in the Week, and every Holiday in the Year. Divided into Two Parts. The Fourth Edition, Corrected. Twelves.</p>
            <p>The preſent State of the Univerſe, or and Account of 1. The Riſe, Births, Names, Matches, Children, and near Allies of all the preſent chief Princes of the World. 2. Their Coats of Arms, Motto's, Devices, Liveries, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions and Languages. 3. The Names of their chief Towns, with ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of the Houſes and Inhabitants, their chief Seats of Pleaſure, and other remarkable Things in their Dominions. 4. Their Revenues, Power and Strength. Alſo and Account of Common-wealths, relating to the ſame Heads. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Edition much amended and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, with the Addition of the Styles or Titles of the ſeveral Potentates and Republicks. Twelves.</p>
            <p>Political and Military Obſervations, Remarks, and Maxims; of <hi>Charles</hi> V. late Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> General of the Emperor's Forces; never Printed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Octavo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Archaeologiae Graecae,</hi> or the Antiquities of <hi>Greece.</hi> Volume the Second, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb facs="tcp:152881:151"/>1. The Military Affairs of the <hi>Grecians.</hi> 2. Some of their Military Cuſtoms. By <hi>John Potter,</hi> M. A. and Fellow of <hi>Lincoln</hi>-College, <hi>Oxon.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>Hiſtory of <hi>Portugal,</hi> from the firſt Ages of the World, to the late great Revolution under King <hi>John</hi> IV. in the Year, 1640. Written in <hi>Spaniſh</hi> by <hi>Emanuel de Faſia y Souſa,</hi> Knight of the Order of Chriſt; Tranſlated and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued down to this preſent Year, 1698. By Captain <hi>John Stevens.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:151"/>
            <head>Books printed for <hi>William Haws,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate-ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Short Diſcourſe upon the Doctrin of our Baptiſmal Covenant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Expoſition upon the Preliminary Queſtions and Anſwers of our Church-Catechiſm, proper to be read by all young Perſons, in order to their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the whole Frame and Tenour of the Chriſtian Religion, and to their being duly prepared for Confirmation; with Devotions preparatory to that Apoſtolick and uſeful Ordinance. By <hi>Thomas Bray,</hi> D. D. The Second Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The great Law of Conſideration, or a Diſcourſe wherein the Nature and Uſefulneſs, and abſolute Neceſſity of Conſideration, in order to a truly ſerious and religious Life, is laid open. The
<pb facs="tcp:152881:152"/>Seventh Edition, Corrected and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. By <hi>Anthony Horneck,</hi> D. D. late Prebendary of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Miniſter of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152881:152"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
